<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge"
         xmlns:call="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge#call"
>
<title>Which Finesse?</title>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<dealer>East</dealer>
<vul>None</vul>
<scoring>Matchpoints</scoring>
<source>San Mateo Bridge Center</source>
<!-- SET00135, hand 8 -->
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="KT7432" he="J9" di="KJ2" cl="Q3"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AJ65" he="AQ" di="876" cl="KJ54"/>
</diagram>
<auction dealer="E">
<call code="P"/> <call code="1N"/> <call code="P"/> <call code="2H"><note>Transfer</note></call>
<call code="P"/> <call code="2S"/> <call code="P"/> <call code="4S"/>
<call code="P"/> <call code="P"/> <call code="P"/>
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
West leads the <diamond card="A"/> and his partner contributes the
four. West shifts to a trump, and you draw trumps in two rounds ending
in hand, then lead a club to the queen.  East wins the ace and leads a
heart.  Should you take the heart finesse at this position?
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="T743" he="J9" di="KJ" cl="3"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="J6" he="AQ" di="87" cl="KJ5"/>
</diagram>
</p><p>
The contract is in the bag. The question is, how can you make
the overtrick?  You have two clubs, a diamond, a heart, and four
spade tricks.  East has cruelly made me make the red-suit decision
now, it seems.
</p><p>
The heart finesse would be 50%, but it is slightly better than 50% that the
<heart card="K"/> and the <diamond card="Q"/> were in different hands.
You play the <heart card="A"/>, cash the <diamond card="K"/> and run
the spades, pitching a diamond and the <heart card="Q"/>.  You reach
this position:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="J" di="J" cl="3"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="" di="" cl="KJ5"/>
</diagram>
If the red suit honors were split among your opponents, then neither could
hold three clubs at this end position.  Even if they weren't split, if
the person with both honors also held four or more clubs at the beginning,
you'd still have that person squeezed.  This makes this line much better
than 50%.
</p><p>
Sometimes, when presented with a choice of two finesses, you should choose
neither.
</p><p>
Technically, this isn't a double squeeze, in that only one person is guarding
clubs.  Still, it operates like a double squeeze.
</p><p>
Incidentally, I found this play at the table, but when I cashed the
<diamond card="K"/>, East's queen dropped.  East also held the
<heart card="K"/> and long clubs, so anything I did, short of taking
the diamond finesse, would have given me the overtrick.  The full deal was:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="KT7432" he="J9" di="KJ2" cl="Q3"/>
<hand seat="W" sp="9" he="8653" di="AT953" cl="T76"/>
<hand seat="E" sp="Q8" he="KT742" di="Q4" cl="A982"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AJ65" he="AQ" di="876" cl="KJ54"/>
</diagram>
West could put pressure on me by continuing diamonds at trick two. 
If he had, I had already decided to fly the king, to avoid losing
four tricks on the hand.
</p><p>
What happens if, after winning the <club card="A"/>, East exits a club?
That then kills the entry for the squeeze above.  Instead, you win
the club return, cash the other top club, the <diamond card="K"/> and
run the spades.  The end position is:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="3" he="J" di="J" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="AQ" di="" cl="5"/>
</diagram>
On the last spade, if East doesn't pitch a club, you pitch the club from
hand.  If neither opponent pitches the <diamond card="K"/>, you play the
heart to the ace, hoping that one of the opponents was forced to bare the king.
</p><p>
This line fails whenever West has the long club and exactly one of the
<diamond card="Q"/> and the <heart card="K"/>, or if he holds the
<heart card="K"/> and no other control.  If either opponent has the
<diamond card="Q"/> and the <heart card="K"/> there is an automatic
squeeze.  If East holds the <heart card="K"/> and the long club,
there is a positional squeeze.
</p><p>
I think this all adds up to more than 50%, but it's difficult to tell
given all the different pieces of information you have so far - for
instance, if East has the <diamond card="Q"/>, why didn't he signal a clear
encouragement?  Tough to figure that kind of thing into probabilistic
analysis.
</p><p>
What happens when West hold the <club card="A"/> and wins the second club?
Obviously, he'll want to exit in clubs or diamonds.  If he exits
with a diamond, you play the <diamond card="K"/>, cross with the 
trump ten, cash the <club card="J"/>, pitching a heart, then run your
trumps.  This reaches the 3-card ending noted above.
</p><p>
Paul Wendt has noted that the defense can break the squeeze if they
hold up the <club card="A"/> twice.  This gambit gets rid of my club
loser, but it fails to give me any more winners, and it keeps me from
rectifying the count for the squeeze.  My best bet is to try both of
the red-suit finesses.  If one of them is on, I've got my overtrick.
If both are on, I've got two overtricks.
</p><p>
But why on earth would either opponent duck the club twice?  I'd be dealing
either with an act of either extreme cunning or extreme stupidity.  Maybe
my opponent is aware that both finesses are offside?
</p><p>
If both red honors are offside, I can only make the overtrick, double-dummy,
if East is holding the <club card="A"/>, via a strip squeeze at this end position:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="^T" he="J9" di="KJ" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W" sp="" he="K8" di="T95" cl=""/>
<hand seat="E" sp="" he="T7" di="Q4" cl="A"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="AQ" di="8^7" cl="J"/>
</diagram>
On the last spade, East clearly can't part with a diamond or the club
ace, so he must part with a heart.  Now I cross to the <heart card="A"/> and
throw East in with the club.</p>
<p>
Perhaps it is right, given that one of my defenders has brilliantly
held up the <club card="A"/>, to play for both finesses offside.  Or maybe
that's just what they want me to think.  I would certainly start
feeling quite paranoid if they ducked clubs twice.
</p><p>
Still, I don't anticipate too many defenders will find that defense.
I know I wouldn't.
</p>
</body></article>
