<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge"
         xmlns:call="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge#call"
>
<title>Anticipation</title>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<scoring>Matchpoints</scoring>
<dealer>North</dealer>
<vul>Both</vul>
<source href="http://www.okbridge.com/">OKbridge</source>
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="T843" he="A8654" di="9" cl="743"/>
<hand seat="E" sp="K62" he="JT932" di="KT8" cl="AK"/>
</diagram>
<auction dealer="N">
<call code="P"/> <call code="1H"/> <call code="1N"/> <call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/> <call code="P"/>
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
Your partner leads the <club card="T"/>.  How do you plan your
defense?
</p><p>
Attacking hearts is probably futile; partner is likely to be void.
</p><p>
Perhaps partner led from <club cards="QT9xx"/> and a side ace? That's a
pipe-dream, of course, but certainly one worth playing for at imps.
</p><p>
Since this is matchpoints, perhaps you should worry about overtricks. 
Assuming declarer has the last three hearts, there is a danger
of declarer squeezing you in hearts and diamonds.
</p><p>
So you win the <club card="A"/> (so partner doesn't get deceived about
the suit) and cash the second club (declarer dropping the jack).
You then lead the <diamond card="T"/> to smother the nine in dummy.
If partner has a diamond card, you might be providing the entry to
his clubs, if he did lead from <club cards="QT9xx"/>.
</p><p>
As it is, declare wins the <diamond card="Q"/>, partner discouraging.
Declarer leads the <spade card="Q"/>, and partner follows low.
What now?
</p><p>
You should duck.  The end position you should fear is:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="A7" di="" cl="^7"/>
<hand seat="W" sp="" he="" di="76" cl="^T"/>
<hand seat="E" sp="" he="JT" di="K" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="8" di="J" cl="^Q"/>
</diagram>
On the play of the last club, you would be squeezed.
</p><p>
For declarer to get to this position, he needs to somehow cash the
fourth spade without using the <heart card="A"/> entry.  He might be
able to do that if you win the <spade card="K"/>, on this deal:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="T843" he="A8654" di="9" cl="743"/>
<hand seat="W" sp="A97" he="" di="76542" cl="T9854"/>
<hand seat="E" sp="K62" he="JT932" di="KT8" cl="AK"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="QJ5" he="KQ8" di="AQJ3" cl="QJ6"/>
</diagram>
</p><p>
If you win the <spade card="K"/> and exit anything, partner is under pressure
to do the right thing when declarer next leads the <spade card="J"/>.  Partner
will have to duck the jack to break up the red suit squeeze against you.
Perhaps he can see that, perhaps not.  In any event, if you duck
the <spade card="Q"/>, you won't have to worry about it.
</p><p>
As it was, you have to lead diamonds at some point to break up
another heart/diamond squeeze, because otherwise declarer could have made the
fourth spade his squeeze card in this position:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="^8" he="86" di="9" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W" sp="" he="" di="76" cl="T9"/>
<hand seat="E" sp="" he="J" di="KT8" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="" di="AQJ3" cl=""/>
</diagram>
On the last spade, you have to either pitch a diamond, giving declarer
three diamond tricks, or the <heart card="J"/>, giving declarer two hearts
and two diamonds.
</p><p>
Declarer can arrive at this position easily, because here he is allowed to
use the <heart card="A"/> entry to finish the spades.
</p><p>
At the beginning, I implied setting up hearts was useless, and that was
correct up to a point, but, in fact, leading hearts at every turn does break
up the squeeze(s).
</p><p>
You win the first club, and fire back a high heart.
</p><p>
Declare attacks spades first.  You win the second spade, fire back
a low heart (which nominally lets declarer win his eight, but that
gives declarer no new tricks.) declarer leads another spade, West winning.
If West exits in clubs, you win and lead a third heart in this position:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="T" he="A86" di="9" cl="7"/>
<hand seat="W" sp="" he="" di="765" cl="T98"/>
<hand seat="E" sp="" he="T92" di="KT8" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="7" di="AQJ3" cl="Q"/>
</diagram>
By putting declarer in dummy before he has cashed his last club,
you have left yourself some room to breath when the fourth spade is
cashed.
</p><p>!
Declarer does no better attacking clubs first, because he can't afford
to cash his established club before allowing your partner in with the spade.
</p><p>
So attacking hearts does work, but I prefer the diamond shift, as it
protects against the red-suit squeezes and the possibility of partner
holding <diamond card="Q"/> and <club cards="QT9xx"/>.
</p><p>
On this deal, you would get about 60% for holding declarer to two,
and 30% for allowing three to make.  Watch out for those overtricks.
</p>
</body>
</article>
