<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge"
         xmlns:call="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge#call"
>
<title>Assumptions</title>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<dealer>South</dealer>
<vul>None</vul>
<scoring>Matchpoints</scoring>
<source href="http://web.mit.edu/mitdlbc/www/home.html">Draper Labs Bridge Club</source>
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="KT9" he="64" di="A53" cl="Q8652"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AJ43" he="K9852" di="K" cl="AKJ"/>
</diagram>
<auction dealer="S">
<call code="1H"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="1N"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="2C"><note>A timid call</note></call>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="2S"><note>Shows clubs and 9-10 pts</note></call>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="3S"><note>Natural</note></call>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="4D"><note>Cue bid</note></call>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="6C"><note>A matchpoint stab, after bypassing <contract code="3N"/>
                     with a double stop in diamonds.</note></call>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
</auction>
<hr/>
<h3> The bidding </h3>
<p>
I have close to the values for a <call code="2S"/> reverse, and I don't have
a problem making a natural reverse here with only four spades, but I was unhappy
about the stiff <diamond card="K"/>, and I prefer to have a better suit when I reverse.
Several people suggest I should have called <call code="2N"/>.
</p><p>
When my partner finally took his <call code="4D"/> cue-bid (a bid I really like, given
his excellent help in the other suits) I found that we had a double-stop
in diamonds and had bypassed <contract code="3N"/>.  I figured that there was no way
<contract code="5C"/> could beat <contract code="3N"/>, so I bid the slam.</p>
<h3> The problem </h3>
<p>West thought long and hard before he passed the <call code="6C"/> bid.  Perhaps he
could tell I was taking a shot, but I was almost sure he had the 
<heart card="A"/>, and probably the <heart card="Q"/> as well.  How could I
make this contract  with the <heart card="A"/> offside?
</p><p>
West led a diamond, which road to my king.  If I played him for the <heart card="A"/>,
it was futile to try to attack hearts.  I needed to pick up the spades
for four tricks, plus two diamonds, a diamond ruff, and five club tricks, to
make twelve.  I had to get to dummy twice, once to ruff diamonds and once
to finish drawing trumps. I couldn't afford to overtake the <club card="J"/>
<em>and</em> ruff a diamond with another club honor, so my two entries
had to be in spades.
</p>
<h3> The plan </h3>
<p>
The plan was, I would lead a low spade to the 10, ruff a diamond,
take the top two clubs, and lead a spade to the nine.  After running the
trumps and cashing the <diamond card="A"/>, I would be pitched down to:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="K" he="64" di="" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="Qx?" he="Ax?" di="" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AJ" he="K" di="" cl=""/>
</diagram>
There would be only two spades outstanding, and West would be marked
with one of them - the queen.  On the lead of the <spade card="K"/>, I'd 
have him. If East followed, I would overtake, dropping the <spade card="Q"/> from West.  If East did not follow, I would play low on the spade,
and then endplay West with a heart to his ace, forcing him
to lead his last spade to my ace.
</p>
<h3>Result</h3>
<p>
Of course, the <spade card="Q"/> was with East, so my plan fell apart
immediately. East fired back a heart through my hand, and I was down
three when East turned up with a stiff heart and four clubs.
</p><p>
Sigh.  At least I was right about the <heart card="A"/>.
</p>
</body>
</article>
