<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge"
         xmlns:call="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge#call"
>
<title>A Best Shot</title>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<dealer>North</dealer>
<vul>N-S</vul>
<scoring>IMPs</scoring>
<source href="http://www.okbridge.com/">OKbridge</source>
<!-- IMP-11.22 -->
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="AQJ" he="" di="KT764" cl="AJT76"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="42" he="AK987532" di="5" cl="85"/>
</diagram>
<auction dealer="N">
<call code="1D"/> <call code="2S"/> <call code="3H"/> <call code="P"/>
<call code="3N"/> <call code="P"/>  <call code="4H"/> <call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>  <call code="P"/>
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
West led a spade, declarer ducked from dummy, and East won the 
<spade card="K"/> and continued the suit.  Declarer then played a
third round of spades, pitching his diamond loser, West ruffing.
</p><p>
West then tried to take his side's diamond tricks, leading the 
<diamond card="Q"/>.  Declarer covered with the <diamond card="K"/>,
East played the ace, and declarer ruffed.
</p><p>
Declarer drew two rounds of trumps, both following.  With West's ruff,
that accounted for all the outside trumps.
</p><p>
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="" di="T74" cl="AJT7"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="98753" di="" cl="85"/>
</diagram>
The declarer I was watching looked at this situation and did not see
his chance for an overtrick.  Instead, he just lead a club to dummy.
He got lucky. West, holding the <club cards="KQ"/>, failed
to split her honors, and declarer made 11 tricks.
</p><p>
But wait, if West has the <club cards="KQ"/>, why play for her
to misdefend?  Instead, play her for the <diamond card="J"/>.  On the run
of the hearts, the situation is:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="" di="T" cl="AJ"/>
<hand seat="W" sp="" he="" di="J" cl="KQ"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="^3" di="" cl="85"/>
</diagram>
On the last heart, West must give up in one of the minors.
</p>
<p>
The full deal was:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="AQJ" he="" di="KT764" cl="AJT76"/>
<hand seat="W" sp="86" he="QJ6" di="QJ93" cl="KQ43"/>
<hand seat="E" sp="KT9753" he="T4" di="A82" cl="92"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="42" he="AK987532" di="5" cl="85"/>
</diagram>
Note that this contract can be set with a <club card="K"/> lead.
</p><p>
It could also have been set with a club shift after the spade
lead.  Declarer would be forced to win in dummy.  In danger of
losing a heart, a diamond, a club and a spade, declarer has to
pitch a minor loser immediately.  If Declarer pitches his diamond
on the third spade, West leads a high club and a third round of
clubs, and East ruffs with the ten, promoting a second trump trick
for the defense.  If Declarer pitches
a club, then West leads a diamond to East's ace and East and
East leads a fourth round of spades, again promoting a second trump
trick for the defense.
</p>
</body>
</article>
