<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>Countless Squeezes</title>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<dealer>North</dealer>
<vul>None</vul>
<scoring>IMPs</scoring>
<source href="http://www.okbridge.com/">OKbridge</source>
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="96" he="KQJT95" di="AT6" cl="74"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AK543" he="A" di="K82" cl="KQ65"/>
</diagram>
<auction dealer="N">
<call code="1H"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="1S"/>
<call code="3C"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="4N"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="5D"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="6N"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<!--
1H     Pass   1S     3C
Pass   Pass   4NT    Pass
5D     Pass   6NT    Pass
Pass   Pass
-->
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
Opening lead: <heart card="8"/>
</p><p>
I was  playing <contract code="6N"/>, a rather awkward slam.  I won the heart with the
ace and led the <club card="K"/>, hoping to rectify the count and
squeeze East in diamonds and spades.  Annoyingly, West wouldn't help
me; after a moment of thought, he ducked the <club card="K"/>.
</p><p>
This put me in a pickle, and the line I chose at the time was basically
to give up, taking my tricks and going home.  I was a wimp, and got what I
deserved.
</p><p>
There are actually a number of lines which give me a chance to make this
contract.
</p><p>
For example, assume West has both diamond honors and at most two spades.
Take the top spades, then play a diamond from hand, finessing if West
doesn't split his honors.  Assuming he does split the diamond honors,
win in dummy, and run the hearts. 
</p><p>
I am in this position:
</p>
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="^K" di="T6" cl="4"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="" he="" di="Qx" cl="AJ"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="5" he="" di="K2" cl="^Q"/>
</diagram>
<p>On the last heart, I pitch the club Q.  Assuming West had at least
six clubs for his call, I know the count in that suit at the end.
If he pitches down to one club, I endplay him in clubs and he is forced
to lead a diamond, giving me two more tricks in the suit.  If he
pitches down to one diamond, I can drop his <diamond card="Q"/>.
</p><p>
This line also works if West started with a stiff diamond honor and
two or fewer spades, because East would be squeezed.
</p><p>
If West started with three or more spades and the <diamond
cards="QJ"/>, and I ascertain this somehow, there is still a squeeze
on this line, but I have to be careful about him coming down to: 
<diagram><hand seat="W" sp="7" he="" di="Q" cl="A"/></diagram>
at the end.  Then when I try to endplay him in clubs, he can 
exit a spade.  If I have reason to believe he is still holding
a spade, I have to play for the diamond drop.
</p><p>
If West has four spades, there is a different squeeze available.  After
he ducks the club, I lead a low diamond to the ten.  Assume that loses to
East, and East continues a spade.  I win, cash <diamond cards="AK"/>
and run the hearts. 
</p><p>
On the last heart, we are at:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="x" he="^5" di="" cl="4"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="xx" he="" di="" cl="A"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="A5" he="" di="" cl="^Q"/>
</diagram>
I pitch the <club card="Q"/> and West must give up in one of the black suits.
</p><p>
Notice how the <club card="4"/> becomes a threat card once I know East has
no more clubs.  West's bid has given me information which I would
not otherwise be able to work out.
</p><p>
Of course, it seems unlikely that West has both diamond honors,
and even more unlikely that West has four spades.  Still, this
second line brings to mind other options.  Notice that even though
the opponents have an ace outstanding, it is safe for me to rectify
the count in another suit as long, as I can lose the trick to East,
because he can't lead a club back.  I might be able to later squeeze
him in spades and diamonds.
</p><p>
Clearly, I need to lose a spade trick to East, because losing a diamond trick
to him gives up my diamond threat.  If he holds the <spade cards="QJT"/>, all I
need to do is lead a low spade to the nine.  His best exit is a diamond
at this point - if he exits in a major suit, for instance, I don't even need
East to hold the diamond guard.  Instead, I execute a double squeeze.
</p><p>
I win his return, and cash the two top spades.  Now I cross to the 
<diamond card="K"/>
and run the hearts, pitching clubs from my hand.  When the last heart is
played, the position is:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="^5" di="T" cl="4"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="" he="" di="Qx" cl="A"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="Q" he="" di="Jx" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="5" he="" di="Ax" cl=""/>
</diagram>
East must pitch a diamond, or I score my <spade card="5"/>.  I pitch my spade,
and West must pitch a diamond or I score the <club card="4"/>.
</p><p>
What if I play <spade card="A"/> then a low spade, to protect against
a stiff queen, jack, or ten in West's hand?  That seems to cause
entry problems if South exits a high diamond.  I win the diamond
in dummy and run the hearts, to this four-card end position:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="^5" di="Tx" cl="4"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="" he="" di="xx" cl="AJ"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="QJ" he="" di="Jx" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="A5" he="" di="Ax" cl=""/>
</diagram>
On the last heart, I need to guess what shape East has pitched down
to.  East might fool me by pitching down to:
<diagram><hand seat="E" sp="QJ7" he="" di="J" cl=""/></diagram>
and yielding the <spade card="J"/> on the last heart.
</p><p>
So are there any other options?  What about a squeeze without rectifying
the count?  Assume East is guarding both diamonds and spades.  After West
ducks the club, I simply cross to the <diamond card="K"/> and run the hearts:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="96" he="^5" di="T6" cl="4"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="Tx" he="" di="xx" cl="AJ"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="QJxx" he="" di="QJ" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AK54" he="" di="A8" cl=""/>
</diagram>
On the last heart, if East pitches a diamond, I get another diamond,
and if East pitches a spade, I pitch a diamond, and play three rounds
of spades, setting up the fourth.  When East is in, he has to lead a diamond
to the ace and my good spade is my twelfth trick.  A good East will put me
to a guess at the end. For example, he might unguard the spades,
pitching down to three early, and then, on the last heart, pitch the 
<diamond card="J"/> from:
<diagram><hand seat="E" sp="QJT" he="" di="QJ9" cl=""/></diagram>
</p><p>
But if West can find the club duck and East can find such a deceptive
sequence of pitches, perhaps I should concede the hand to their superior
skill.
</p><p>
For a hand I gave up on, there certainly were quite a few options.
</p>
</body>
</article>
