<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge"
         xmlns:call="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge#call"
>
<title>Down Three is Good Bridge?</title>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<dealer>South</dealer>
<vul>None</vul>
<scoring>IMPs</scoring>
<source href="http://www.okbridge.com/">OKbridge</source>
<!-- (IMP-39.103, 1995)-->
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="8762" he="" di="JT542" cl="9874"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="K" he="Q8" di="AKQ973" cl="A532"/>
</diagram>
<auction dealer="S">
<call code="1D"/>
<call code="1S"/>
<call code="3D"><note>Weak</note></call>
<call code="4H"/>

<call code="5C"><note>Lead directing?</note></call>
<call code="6H"/>
<call code="7D"/>
<call code="X"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<!--
South   West    North   East
1D      1S      3D(a)   4H        (a) Preemptive
5C(b)   6H      7D      X         (b) Lead directing(?)
All Pass
-->
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
West led a low heart, ruffed in dummy.  What is the best line for declarer?
</p><p>
Declarer's goal is to go down as little as possible.  If clubs split 3-2,
declarer loses a spade and two clubs.  What if they split 4-1?  Declarer
has a chance to endplay whoever holds the stiff, if that stiff is not the
six.
</p><p>
Declarer should immediately lose a spade to West.  If West
finds the club continuation, all is lost, but he is unlikely to
find it ; if he holds something like <club cards="KQJ6"/> or
<club cards="QJT6"/>, he'd have to find the lead of the 
<club card="6"/> to still get
three tricks in the suit, and if he holds the stiff, he will be 
hard-pressed to lead  into your presumed club strength.
</p><p>
So, assume that West exits a heart.  Ruff in dummy, ruff a spade high,
lead a diamond to the ten, ruff another spade high, a diamond
to the jack and ruff another spade high.  Now lead a low club from hand
at this position:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="" di="5" cl="9874"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="" di="9" cl="A53^2"/>
</diagram>
</p><p>
If one of the defenders holds a stiff club other than the 6, he will be endplayed, forced
to concede a ruff-and-sluff.  And if his partner overtakes the club, declarer
can duck a club continuation and, if clubs were 4-1, the defender on lead again
has to yield either a ruff-and-discard or lead a club from, say, 
<club cards="K6"/>, while declarer still has <club cards="A5"/>
opposite <club cards="98"/>.
</p><p>
This line, protecting against most 4-1 breaks, allows declarer to be down only
3, for -500.  This is still not likely to be a great results, as many pairs
will not likely find the heart slam (diamonds are 0-2, with West
holding the <spade card="A"/>, so the slam makes.) Still -500 would
have been worth about 6 IMPs more than -800, against the +480 at the
other table.
</p>
</body>
</article>
