<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>A Nice Endplay</title>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<dealer>West</dealer>
<vul>Both</vul>
<scoring>IMPs</scoring>
<source href="http://www.okbridge.com/">OKbridge</source>
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="85" he="654" di="Q8752" cl="AT7"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AJT962" he="KJ2" di="A" cl="K53"/>
</diagram>
<auction dealer="W">
<call code="3H"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="3S"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
West leads the <club card="J"/>.  Now, how are you going to make this
contract?
</p><p>
It looks like you have three heart losers, a club loser and at least
one spade loser.
</p><p>
Larry Weil (larry), of Cambridge MA, guessed spades right, and
found a nice endplay to make his contract.
</p><p>
He won the club lead in dummy, and played the <spade card="8"/> from dummy,
ducked all around.  Another spade was led, to East's queen and Larry's
ace, West following small.
</p><p>
Larry then cashed the <diamond card="A"/> before throwing East in with the
third round of trumps.  East, stuck with the lead and no hearts to his name,
had no satisfying exit.
</p><p>
If he led a low diamond, Larry would pitch a small heart from his hand,
and, if West won, West would be endplayed (assuming West's <club card="J"/> was a singleton.)
</p><p>
If he led the <diamond card="K"/>, Larry would again pitch a heart, and East
would have to give up a trick in whichever minor he led next.
</p><p>
In practice, East led a low club, which Larry allowed to ride to the
ten in dummy, giving him his ninth trick.
</p><p>
Notice that West's bidding and lead allowed Larry to make the inferences
necessary to bring this contract home.  Without the bidding, the auction
might likely go 1<spade/>-1NT-3<spade/>-Pass, and Larry would have had no
guide on how to play the hand.
</p><p>
Also, notice East made a fatal error by not splitting his honors
in trumps.  In this case, he needed to split his honors simply to
preserve his small trump as an exit card.
</p><p>
Richard Pavlicek has noted, via email, that declarer can still make
with an endplay if East splits his honors.  Declarer plays the ace,
and exits with the trump jack.  East wins and exits with a trump.
</p><p>
Declarer cashes his <diamond card="A"/> and runs all of the spades leading
to this position on the last spade:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="6^5" di="Q8" cl="T7"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="" he="AQT^9" di="xx" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="^2" he="KJ2" di="" cl="K5"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="" he="" di="Kx" cl="Q9xx"/>
<!--
             S: -
             H: 6*5*
             D: Q8
             C: T7

S:  -                       S:  - 
H: AQT*9*                   H:  - 
D: xx                       D: Kx
C:  -                       C: Q9xx

             S: *2*
             H: KJ2
             D:  - 
             C: K5
-->
</diagram>
</p>
<p>
If East pitches a club, declarer plays the <club card="K"/> and another club,
and East must give up a diamond at the end.
</p><p>
If East pitches a diamond, declarer plays the <heart card="K"/> to West, who
is then endplayed into leading diamonds, which forces East to lead clubs -
a stepping-stone endplay!
</p>
</body>
</article>
