<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge"
         xmlns:call="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge#call"
>
<title>An Intriguing Trump Squeeze</title>
<body>
<diagram id="start">
<header>
<dealer>North</dealer>
<vul>Both</vul>
<scoring>Matchpoints</scoring>
<source href="http://www.okbridge.com/">OKbridge</source>
<!-- (MP-38.38, 1995) -->
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="KQ64" he="A53" di="AQ98" cl="K8"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="" he="KJ876" di="K74" cl="AJ763"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="J983" he="4" di="T52" cl="QT542"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AT752" he="QT92" di="J63" cl="9"/>
</diagram>
<auction dealer="N">
<call code="1C"><note>Precision</note></call>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="1S"/>
<call code="2H"/>

<call code="3H"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="3N"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="4D"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="4S"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<!--
North   East    South   West
1C(*)	Pass	1S      2H           (*) Precision
3H      Pass    3NT     Pass
4D      Pass    4S      All pass
-->
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
From the start, it looked like declarer should be able to make an
overtrick, but Ruoyo Fan (FrANcis on okbridge) found an imaginative
line to make two overtricks after a favorable diamond lead.
</p><p>
You can't really blame West for leading a diamond - with South bidding
notrump, a heart lead seems unappetizing, and a club lead looks riskier
than the diamond lead.
</p><p>
Fan won the diamond lead in hand with the jack (East playing the ten.)
When he led a low trump to the queen, West showed out.  Fan then drew
trumps (finessing against East's jack), and West pitched three clubs and a
diamond.  Fan led a diamond, dropping West's now stiff diamond,
and Fan played two more top diamonds, allowing him to pitch his club.
</p><p>
Here is the position on the last diamond from North:
<diagram original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="A53" di="^9" cl="K8"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="" he="KJ87" di="" cl="AJ"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="" he="4" di="" cl="QT54^2"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="7" he="QT92" di="" cl="^9"/>
</diagram>
If West pitched a club, Fan would ruff a club, establishing the 
<club card="K"/>,
then lead the <heart card="Q"/>, forcing West to cover.  Whatever he
West did, West would get only one trick.
</p><p>
So West must pitch a heart.
</p><p>
Fan now led a low heart to the nine and jack, and West was stuck.
Here is the situation West was confronted with:
<diagram original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="A5" di="" cl="K8"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="" he="K7" di="" cl="AJ"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="" he="" di="" cl="QT54"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="7" he="QT2" di="" cl=""/>
</diagram>
If West led the <club card="A"/>, Fan would ruff, and lead the 
<heart card="Q"/>.
Whether West covered or not, declarer would have two hearts and the 
<club card="K"/> left.  If he led a low heart, Fan would let it ride to the
<heart card="Q"/>, play a heart to the ace, dropping the king, and ruff a club
to get back to the long heart.  The <heart card="K"/> is obviously
a poor choice of exits - declarer's hand becomes good on that lead.
If West led a low club, Fan would win in dummy, pitching a heart,
ruff a club, and take the heart finesse for the rest of the tricks.
</p><p>
West can't afford to duck the heart lead, either, because then Fan
just plays ace and another heart, setting up the fourth heart with the
trump left as an entry.
</p><p> 
This is some netherworld trump squeeze throw-in.  The <spade card="7"/> 
serves three functions.  First, it forces West to pitch down to three hearts
on the last diamond, to protect against his <club card="A"/> being ruffed out.  Then, 
after he is forced to win a heart, it is protection against West
playing the <club card="A"/>. Lastly it provides a much-needed entry, either
to the long heart or to take the heart finesse, depending on how West chooses
to exit.
</p><p>
Making six was worth 88%, while making five would have been worth 63%.
</p><p>
So, we get back to my pet peeve.  Why is West bidding?  NS almost
certainly have a spade fit, and they have surely just found it.
The <call code="1S"/> bid (light this time) forces the precision
players to game;
the last thing West wants to do is steer them towards a 3NT game
when they have only a modest fit - the trump break could kill them
in 4S.  And if partner is on lead against 3NT, it is far from clear
that West wants a heart lead.
</p><p>
I can certainly see the temptation of bidding on this hand, but I have
learned to also see the temptation of passing.  Like a person who is
cutting back on salt, I have learned the subtle flavor of passing can
often be far more satisfying than the salty flavor of bidding.
</p>
</body>
</article>
