<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>A Familiar Combination</title>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<dealer>East</dealer>
<vul>Both</vul>
<scoring>IMPs</scoring>
<source href="http://www.okbridge.com/">OKbridge</source>
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="AT73" he="T82" di="AJ3" cl="KJ5"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="J985" he="74" di="K92" cl="Q874"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="Q2" he="J3" di="T874" cl="A9632"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="K64" he="AKQ965" di="Q65" cl="T"/>
</diagram>
<hr/>
<p>
Out of the 39 tables that played this hand, 12 North/South pairs bid
to <contract code="6H"/>, and of those, nine made.  (Another two pairs ended up
in <contract code="6N"/>, making.)  Six hearts is not a slam I'd want to bid.
</p><p>
The unfortunate pair I watched played in the more reasonable <contract code="4H"/>
contract.  While dummy joined us in spectator mode, we commiserated,
and one of the other spectators said, "Six hearts doesn't make without
help from the defense."   While most who made <contract code="6H"/> seemed to have some
defensive help, dummy and I disagreed.
</p><p>
Any long-time reader of these web pages will spot the ubiquitous 
<holding cards="AJx"/> opposite <holding cards="Qxx"/> combination.
A good start. 
</p><p>
Assume a trump lead.  Declarer draws trumps in two rounds, and ducks
the <club card="T"/> to East's ace.  East is stuck for a decent exit, but,
in fact, his best exit is a diamond.  Declarer wins dummy's jack, pitches
a spade on the <club card="K"/>, and the plays three rounds of spades,
ruffing the third round, declarer runs trumps, leaving this end position at
the second to last trump:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="7" he="" di="A3" cl="J"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="J" he="" di="K9" cl="Q"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="^65" di="Q6" cl=""/>
</diagram>
West must either pitch his top spade, his top club, or unguard his 
<diamond card="K"/>.  This squeeze operates a trick early because West is
guarding three suits. West can delay the squeeze one trick later by
covering the <club card="T"/> with the queen at trick three, but he cannot
avoid being squeezed in diamonds and spades.
</p>
</body>
</article>
