<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>A Daring Play</title>
<body>
<h2>By Alan Reynolds</h2>
<diagram>
<header>
<vul>N-S</vul>
<scoring>IMP Pairs</scoring>
<source href="http://www.ecatsbridge.com/">ECats Bridge</source>
<!-- IMP-11.22 -->
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="AKJ2" he="AK3" di="T852" cl="Q6"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="76" he="QJ82" di="AK973" cl="KT"/>
<!-- 
                                                             S  AKJ2
                                                             H  AK3
                                                             D  10853
                                                             C  Q6
 
                                                             S  76
                                                             H  QJ82
                                                             D  AK973
                                                             C  K 10
-->
</diagram>
<p> 
I was left to play <call code="4H"/> as South. While <call
code="3N"/> looks to be the room contract, <call code="4H"/>
is all but solid and could gain against bad breaks.
</p>
<p> 
The <card code="D6"/> lead looked to be singleton. I won the jack
with the ace, cashed the <card code="HQ"/>, crossed to <card code="HK"/>
and played the <card code="HA"/>. All followed. This is not
good; playing in hearts I could deal with 1-3 diamonds and 5-1 hearts
[by using diamonds as trump substitutes] to beat the pairs in
<call code="3N"/>.
</p>
<p>
When I led the <card code="DT"/>, east covered with the queen, I won the
king, and west followed.
</p>
<p> 
This is disastrous, all the pairs in <call code="3N"/> - no doubt
the popular contract - will score 12 tricks by default.
</p>
<p>
I must confess that at this point I consoled myself with the thought
that at least we beat those in <call code="5D"/>, cleared a club trick
and claimed 12. 
It was later in the bar when we almost glossed over the hand as a
bidding view that the answer jumped off the page.
</p>
<p> 
At the point where both red suits are known to split you have:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="AKJ2" he="" di="85" cl="Q6"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="76" he="J" di="973" cl="KT"/>
</diagram>
</p>
<p>
Eleven tricks on top and a high club to force the twelfth, 
but this will lose to all the pairs in 3NT.  What can be done?
Take the Spade finesse!
</p>
<p> 
This is a true non-material finesse. Twelve tricks were available
before the play and only twelve are available after. The difference is
that now the tricks can be cashed without giving up the lead. After the
finesse, run the diamonds then the last heart:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="AK2" he="" di="" cl="^Q"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="7" he="^J" di="" cl="KT"/>
</diagram>
This results in an automatic squeeze against either defender holding 
<card code="CA"/> and long spades.
</p>
<p> 
Should the play be found? Yes. The field contract rates to be 
<call code="3N"/>
which makes 12 tricks on any lead for 490. If the finesse works
and the squeeze is on you score 510, if the finesse works and the
squeeze fails your partner will look quizzical but you still come
to 12 tricks and if the finesse fails you lose a point to all those
in 4H and two points to all those in 3NT making 11 tricks. These
rate to be minority groups.
</p>
<p>
The (IMP pairs) scores on the day:
<pre> 
	 4H+1    608
	 4H+2    835
	3NT+3   1318
	 4H+3   1715
	  TOP   3018
</pre>
</p>
</body>
</article>
