<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>Hope Springs Eternal</title>
<date>July 13, 1997</date>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<dealer>North</dealer>
<vul>Both</vul>
<scoring>IMPs</scoring>
<source href="http://www.okbridge.com/">OKbridge</source>
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="AQ83" he="Q9654" di="J4" cl="Q5"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="K5" he="JT3" di="AKQ85" cl="AKJ"/>
</diagram>
<!--
             S: AQ82
             H: Q9654
             D: J4
             C: Q5


             S: K5
             H: JT3
             D: AKQ85
             C: AKJ
-->
<auction dealer="N">
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="2C"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="2H"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="2N"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="3C"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="3D"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="3S"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="3N"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="4N"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="6N"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>

<!--
          North   South
          Pass    2C
          2H      2NT
          3C      3D
          3S      3NT
          4NT     6NT
-->
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
I am not sure I follow this auction to <contract code="6N"/>, but it is
obviously a less-than-perfect contract.
</p><p>
It would appear the only chance for a twelfth trick is if one defender
has the <holding cards="S:JT9"/>, allowing declarer to set up the
<spade card="8"/>.
</p><p>
Brian Storey (CDundee on okbridge) found a solution which took
into account that the defense was not looking at his hand.  He knew
he had two heart losers, but the defense did not.
</p><p>
Brian got a neutral club lead, which he won in hand and imediately
led a heart to the queen.  West played low and East won the king.  East
chose to exit a low diamond, and declarer was able to make his slam.  West
had started with:
<hand sp="T963" he="A72" di="72" cl="T642"/>.
On the run of Brian's winners, West was squeezed in spades and hearts.
The end position was:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="AQ82" he="^9" di="" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="T963" he="A" cl="" di=""/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="J74" he="8" cl="^9" di=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="K5" he="JT" di="^5" cl=""/>
</diagram>
<!--
             S: AQ82
             H: *9*
             D: -
             C: -

S: T963                       S: J74
H: A                          H: -
D: -                          D: -
C: -                          C: x

             S: K5
             H: JT
             D: *5*
             C: -
-->
</p><p>
On the last diamond, West had to keep the <heart card="A"/>, so he must
pitch a spade, and Brian gets four spades.
</p><p>
In this case, the rather clumsy auction probably helped declarer - West
can avoid the squeeze by flying the ace and exiting in any suit, but
West was probably nervous that declarer might be leading low from 
<holding cards="Kx"/> - playing the ace might give declarer a running heart
suit.
</p><p>
From Brian's point of view, it was likely that the heart honors were
split. West would certainly double and lead the
suit if he held them both, and, since dummy's first bid
suit was hearts, East could have doubled to
request a heart lead.  So the only real danger
for Brian is that one of the opponents wins the
heart and leads another heart.  That's a difficult play to find
in this instance.
</p>
</body>
</article>
