<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge"
         xmlns:call="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge#call"
>
<title>Overtricked</title>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<dealer>West</dealer>
<vul>None</vul>
<scoring>Matchpoints</scoring>
<source href="http://www.okbridge.com/">OKbridge</source>
<!-- (MP-46.65, 1995) -->
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="J6" he="KT54" di="K53" cl="A832"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AKT73" he="J" di="AQ98" cl="QT4"/>
</diagram>
<auction dealer="W">
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="1S"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="2N"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="3D"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="3H"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="4S"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<!--
West    North   East    South
Pass    Pass    Pass     1S
Pass    2NT     Pass     3D
Pass    3H      Pass     4S
-->
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
It's not clear why partner didn't bid <call code="3N"/> over <call code="3D"/>, but here you are,
playing an awkward <contract code="4S"/> contract.  To beat the field at matchpoint, you
have to make one more trick than the rest of the field in notrump - that's
a rather tall order.
</p><p>
West leads the <club card="9"/>, you play low from dummy and East wins the club
king.  To your surprise, he shifts to the <diamond card="6"/>, you play the 8,
West plays the jack and you win the king.
</p><p>
You lead the <spade card="J"/> off dummy, which loses to West's queen, and West
comes back with a diamond to East's ten and your ace.  Well, that clears
up that suit.  You draw three rounds of trumps, showing West to have
started with four trumps.  You now run your diamond and spade winners,
pitching hearts from dummy at this position:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="K" di="" cl="A83"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="^3" he="J" di="" cl="QT"/>
</diagram>
On the last spade, if West started with the <heart card="A"/> and four clubs,
he is squeeze.  Even after you pitch the <heart card="K"/> from dummy, if East
started with four clubs and the AQ of hearts, he is squeezed.  You also
make five if clubs split 3-3, of course.
</p><p>
The declarer I watched play this hand found another way to make the
overtrick - after drawing trumps, he led the <heart card="J"/> from
hand, and West, holding <heart cards="Axxx"/> decided to give declarer
a guess, and played low.  Declarer guessed right.
</p><p>
This is a blind spot I personally have as a declarer - I rarely assume that
my opponents will misdefend, even when the correct defense might be
difficult to find.  Still, this time it is wrong to play for the misdefense.
It only does better when West has the <heart card="A"/>, not the queen, two or fewer
clubs, and chooses to play low.  In all other circumstances, the squeeze
does as well or better.
</p><p>
Making five was worth 88.5%, making four would have been very close to 50%.
</p>
</body>
</article>
