<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge"
         xmlns:call="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge#call"
>
<title>Wishful Thinking</title>
<date>Added July 15, 1996</date>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<dealer>West</dealer>
<vul>N/S</vul>
<scoring>IMPs</scoring>
<source href="http://www.okbridge.com/">OKbridge</source>
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="A732" he="AJ2" di="K" cl="AJ974"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="KJ" he="K95" di="A987" cl="QT83"/>
</diagram>
<auction dealer="W">
<call code="2S"/>
<call code="3C"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="3N"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="6N"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="P"/>

<!--
West    North   East    South
2S	3C	Pass    3NT
Pass    6NT     All pass
-->
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
Okay, I said I was not going to manufacture hands, but I saw an
inkling of something interesting in a hand today, and created
this hand to illustrate the point.
</p><p>
This contract is what you deserve for not supporting partner.  
6 <club/> was an easy contract, but you've stumbled into an awkward notrump
slam. 
</p><p>
West starts with a surprising lead, the <diamond card="Q"/>.   You know
West's style, and, in particular, after this lead you strongly suspect
that East holds the <heart card="Q"/> and the <club card="K"/>.
Is there any way to salvage this contract?
</p><p>
There is, if West holds the <heart card="T"/> along with the rest of the
high diamonds.  You win the lead in dummy and start playing clubs.
</p><p>
East wins the <club card="K"/> at some point.  You win East's spade return
in hand, and run the rest of your clubs.
</p><p>
At the last club you have reached this position:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="A72" he="AJ2" di="" cl="^A"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="QT" he="T85" di="JT" cl=""/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="" he="Q75" di="654^3" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="J" he="K95" di="A9^8" cl=""/>
</diagram>
You pitch a diamond, and West is stuck with an awkward decision.
</p><p>
If he chooses his "obvious" discard of a heart, you play the 
<heart card="A"/> and <heart card="J"/>, smothering West's 
<heart card="T"/>.  Whether East covers or not, you win the third
heart in hand, on which trick West is squeezed in spades and diamonds.
</p><p>
If West pitches a diamond, you cash the <spade card="A"/>, then lead the
<heart card="J"/>.  East must cover, to keep you from making three heart
tricks. You cash the <diamond cards="A9"/>, and West is caught in a major
suit squeeze.
</p><p>
A spade pitch gives you three spade tricks, plus two hearts and a diamond.
</p><p>
So, maybe the spade switch by East was the problem.  What happens
if he continues diamonds when he is in with the <club card="K"/>?
</p><p>
You'd be forced to pitch a heart from dummy then run the clubs, 
reaching this position:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="A732" he="AJ" di="" cl="^A"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="QT8" he="T85" di="T" cl=""/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="4" he="Q74" di="65^4" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="KJ" he="K95" di="9^8" cl=""/>
</diagram>
If West pitches a spade, you have four spade tricks and two hearts.
If West pitches a heart, you play the <heart cards="AJ"/>, pinning
the <heart card="T"/>.  If East covers, you simply cash the <heart card="9"/>,
and West is again caught in a diamond-spade squeeze.  If East doesn't
cover, you still have a spade entry to hand to cash the <heart card="K"/>,
again squeezing West.
</p><p>
If West pitches a diamond, you again play the <heart cards="AJ"/>. East
is forced to cover, or you have three heart tricks, a diamond, and two
spades.  You win, and, on playing the diamond winner, West is caught
in a major suit squeeze again.
</p><p>
This is a repeating squeeze (sometimes called a progressive squeeze),
which provides you two extra tricks.
If West ungaurds the spades, you get two tricks immediately.
If he ungaurds hearts or diamonds, West will be caught in a simple squeeze
in the other two suits.
</p><p>
The basic repeating squeeze ending would look something like:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="A72" he="2" di="" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="QT" he="T" di="J" cl=""/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="" he="74" di="62" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="J" he="9" di="9" cl="A"/>
</diagram>
When South plays the <club card="A"/> here, West is caught.  As above, if
West pitches the spade declarer has three spade tricks, while
a red-suit pitch gives declarer one trick immediately, and another
via a simple squeeze in the other two suits.
</p><p>
This basic squeeze position can't be reached in our original deal,
because the squeeze card (the last club) is in the hand with the
long spade suit.
</p><p>
Normally, if we give a squeezed hand even better cards, he is squeezed
again.  On this hand, parodoxically, if West started with the 
<holding cards="H:Qxx"/>, the squeeze is ineffective.  Switching the
<heart card="Q"/> and the <heart card="T"/>, we get this position:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="A72" he="AJ2" di="" cl="^A"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="QT" he="Q85" di="JT" cl=""/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="" he="T74" di="654^3" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="J" he="K95" di="A9^8" cl=""/>
</diagram>
Again, West cannot pitch a spade or a diamond on the club,
but the heart pitch is now safe.  It gives declarer a third trick in hearts,
but he must win the third heart in dummy, and therefore, when that
time comes, West can safely pitch a diamond.
</p><p>
Of course, if West had the <heart card="Q"/>, declarer could make simply 
by finessing in hearts and then running a squeeze in spades and diamonds.
</p><p>
Why, you might ask, must you not take the club finesse, to give yourself
another chance?  It's a case of limited entries.
</p><p>
If you lead a spade to the king and then take
the club finesse, East will exit in diamonds.  You will be at this
uncomfortable crossroad:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="A72" he="AJ2" di="" cl="AJ97"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="QTxxx" he="T85" di="J^T" cl=""/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="" he="Qxxx" di="xxx^x" cl="xx"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="J" he="K95" di="^A98" cl="T8x"/>
</diagram>
What would you pitch from dummy under the <diamond card="A"/>?  
With the <spade card="K"/>
still in your hand, you could safely pitch a heart from dummy.  But
here that isn't so safe.  When you play the last club, West can pitch
a heart.  When you play the <heart cards="AJ"/>, East will
obstinately refuse to cover.  The <heart card="K"/> would now be good, but
you'd have no entry to cash it and effect the spade-diamond squeeze.
</p><p>
Clearly, you can't pitch a club, and if you pitch a spade, your spade
suit will only be a threat to take one trick, and West can ungaurd it
freely, giving you one extra trick, but breaking up the progressive
aspect of the squeeze.  On the last spade, West will be pitching
after you do.
</p><p>
Okay, what if, at trick two, you lead the <heart card="J"/>, forcing East
to cover.  You win the king and take the club finesse.  East wins
and exits a spade:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="A732" he="A2" di="" cl="AJ97"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="QTxxx" he="T85" di="JT" cl=""/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="^x" he="xxx" di="xxxx" cl="xx"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="KJ" he="95" di="A98" cl="T8x"/>
</diagram>
Now, whether you play the spade king or jack , your entries are
all tangled up.  The <spade card="K"/> is a disaster, because you now
have no entry to your hand.  Therefore, you play the 
<spade card="J"/>, West covers, and you win the ace.  You then run
your clubs:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="732" he="A2" di="" cl="^J"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="T8" he="T8" di="JT" cl=""/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="" he="xx" di="xxx^x" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="J" he="95" di="A9^8" cl=""/>
</diagram>
It looks like West is caught in the repeating sqeeze again, but the
entries are all wrong.  West can not pitch a diamond or spade, but
again, the heart pitch is safe, because there are no link cards
for the spade-diamond squeeze.
</p><p>
Clearly, this is a delicate hand.
</p><p>
One last thought.  This line works really only if West's hand was
one of the following:
<handlist>
<hand sp="Qxxxxx" he="Txx" di="QJTx" cl=""><handhead>(A)</handhead></hand>
<hand sp="Qxxxxx" he="Txx" di="QJT" cl="x"><handhead>(B)</handhead></hand>
<hand sp="Qxxxxx" he="Tx" di="QJT" cl="xx"><handhead>(C)</handhead></hand>
<hand sp="Qxxxxx" he="Tx" di="QJTx" cl="x"><handhead>(D)</handhead></hand>
<hand sp="Qxxxxx" he="Txxx" di="QJT" cl=""><handhead>(E)</handhead></hand>
</handlist>
<!--
     (A)             (B)              (C)              (D)
  S: Qxxxxx       S: Qxxxxx        S: Qxxxxx        S: Qxxxxx
  H: Txx          H: Txx           H: Tx            H: Tx
  D: QJTx         D: QJT           D: QJT           D: QJTx
  C:  -           C: x             C: xx            C: x

     (E)     
  S: Qxxxxx 
  H: Txxx  
  D: QJT  
  C:  - 
-->
Note that in (C) and (D), West is not really squeezed - he was dealt
unguarded hearts.
</p><p>
The problem is that declarer will have to make up his mind at the 
6-card end position.  It will be pretty obvious if West pitches
aways his spades.  But what if West pitches away a high diamond?
This is, in fact, a case where the false card is mandatory.  West
only needs one trick, and the void in dummy means that pitching
a high diamond can't do any harm.  If West ever pitches a low diamond
ever, declarer is going to get the hand right.
</p>
</body>
</article>
