<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>A Recovery</title>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<dealer>West</dealer>
<vul>None</vul>
<scoring>IMPs</scoring>
<source href="http://www.okbridge.com/">OKbridge</source>
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="2" he="AK732" di="AKQ3" cl="AQ2"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AK93" he="T5" di="T982" cl="J94"/>
</diagram>
<auction dealer="W">
<call code="P"/>
<call code="1H"/>
<call code="1S"/>
<call code="1N"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="3D"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="3N"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="4N"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="P"/>
<!--
West     North    East     South
Pass     1H       1S       1NT
Pass     3D       Pass     3NT
Pass     4NT      All Pass
-->
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
I won the opening spade lead in my hand.  It doesn't take a genius to realize
that all I really needed to do was take the club finesse, and, whether it won
or lost, score two clubs, two spades, two hearts, and, assuming diamonds
broke, four diamonds.
</p><p>
Perhaps it was the potential missed <contract code="6D"/> slam which hindered my thinking.
Perhaps I was trying to make <contract code="6N"/>. Whatever the reason, on the second trick,
I ducked a heart to East.  East returned a low spade, and West won and
continued spades, which I won, having pitched a heart and a club from dummy.
</p><p>
Disheartened, I played the top diamonds with West showing out on the third
round.  Well, at least they split.  If hearts split also, I'd still
make this contract, even after my initial misplay.  When I played off
the top hearts, I got bad news. West showed out on the third round.
</p><p>
Somewhere, out of the fog that was my brain, I started counting.
East started with four hearts, five spades (presumably, from the bidding),
and three diamonds, and thus only one club.  Aha! I played the <club card="A"/> ,
planning to play the queen to West's king.  Instead, I dropped East's stiff
king, which allowed me to make an overtrick.
</p><p>
Phew.
</p>
</body>
</article>
