<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge"
         xmlns:call="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge#call"
>
<title>Lucky Break</title>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<dealer>West</dealer>
<vul>N/S</vul>
<scoring>Matchpoints</scoring>
<source href="http://www.okbridge.com/">OKbridge</source>
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="8754" he="87" di="AKJ762" cl="K"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AK6" he="AQT32" di="Q3" cl="985"/>                              
</diagram>
<auction dealer="W">
<call code="P"/>
<call code="1D"/>
<call code="X"/>
<call code="XX"/>

<call code="2C"/>
<call code="2D"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="2H"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="3D"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="3N"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<!--
West   North  East   South
Pass   1D     Dbl    Redbl
2C     2D     Pass   2H
Pass   3D     Pass   3NT
All Pass
-->
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
Our auction was less than successful, and West started ominously,
leading a club to East's ace.  After taking the <club cards="QJ"/>
(with me pitching spades from dummy),
a wonderful thing occurred - East shifted to the
<spade card="Q"/>.  Apparently, the clubs were blocked.  Hallelujah!  Now
I could even make 10 tricks. Sure, I could have taken the nearly marked
heart finesse, but on okbridge, you never know whether East has the
full strength for his takeout double.  It was matchpoints, so I
considered risking it anyway, in an attempt to beat those in five diamonds
making six.
</p><p>
But instead, I decided to play for a showup squeeze, playing for
East to have four or more spades.
</p><p>
I played the <spade cards="AK"/>, and ran the diamonds.
The end position, with one diamond to go, was:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="87" di="2" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="" he="??" di="" cl="T"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="Q" he="??" di="" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="6" he="AQ" di="" cl=""/>
</diagram>
</p><p>      
On the last diamond, East must either give up a heart, or his high
spade.  If he gives up a heart, I pitch my spade and play a low heart
to the ace.  If East pitches a spade, my spade is good.  If East had
started with
<hand sp="QJxx" he="Jxxxx" di="x" cl="AQJ"/>, then my line would drop West's
stiff <heart card="K"/>, which would make me look like a genius.
</p><p>
Often, the showup squeeze at matchpoints is a big win - it gives you
a chance for an overtrick without the risk of taking a losing finesse
and going down.  And occasionally you drop an honor offside.
</p><p>
In reality, the East/West hands were:
<diagram>
<hand seat="W" sp="T3" he="95" di="985" cl="T76432"/>
<hand seat="E" sp="QJ92" he="KJ64" di="T4" cl="AQJ"/>
</diagram>

and when East didn't pitch the high spade, my heart felled his
K.  On this hand, I might as well have finessed, but next time...
</p>
</body>
</article>
