<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge"
         xmlns:call="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge#call"
>
<title>Stripped</title>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<dealer>North</dealer>
<vul>E/W</vul>
<scoring>Matchpoints</scoring>
<source href="http://www.accesscom.com/~unit503/">Palo Alto Bridge Club</source>
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="KT74" he="6" di="T832" cl="AK98"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="Q862" he="T832" di="J76" cl="43"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="AJ5" he="KQ954" di="" cl="QJT65"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="93" he="AJ7" di="AKQ954" cl="72"/>
</diagram>
<auction dealer="N">
<call code="1C" comment="?"/>
<call code="1H"/>
<call code="2D"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="3D"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="3N"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<!--
North   East    South   West
1C(?)   1H      2D      Pass
3D      Pass    3NT     All Pass
-->
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
West led the <heart card="2"/>.  While tabling dummy,  my partner said,
"You have a right to be mad."
</p><p>
What he didn't know was that I was looking at nine top tricks.
This being a matchpoints event, it was time to start thinking about
overtricks.
</p><p>
East played the <heart card="Q"/>, which I ducked.  East thought for
a moment, then switched to the <club card="Q"/>.  I ducked again.  East
continued with the <club card="J"/>, which I won.  I cashed my second high
club, West showing out, and ran the diamonds.  West started with
all three diamonds, so East had to find six pitches.
</p><p>
Against me, East pitched all of his hearts, perhaps playing his partner
for the <heart card="J"/> (not unreasonable, given that West led a <em>low</em> heart,
but then, why didn't East continue hearts after the first trick?)
</p><p>
But even if East pitches perfect, I can make the overtrick.  East must
hold the <spade card="A"/> and two hearts at this end-position:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="KT" he="" di="" cl="9"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="A" he="K9" di="" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="9" he="AJ" di="" cl=""/>
</diagram>
At this point, I lead a low spade from both hands, East's ace wins,
and he must lead a heart for me to finesse.
</p><p>
Of course, I don't know for sure that East has the <spade card="A"/>,
but when I run the diamonds, East will be forced to hold two hearts, and,
if he holds the <spade card="A"/>, he with have to pitch away <em>all</em>
of his clubs. If he doesn't hold the <spade card="A"/>, he will probably pitch away all 
of his spades, instead.
</p><p>
So when East pitches all of his club, I will play him for the <spade card="A"/>,
and nail him.  And if East was brilliant enough to pitch all of his
clubs when he didn't hold the <spade card="A"/>, I would congratulate him on
his fine defense, and move on.
</p><p>
In retrospect, I don't think much of my bidding.  Partner might well
have the <spade card="A"/>, rather than the <spade card="K"/>, and then
<contract code="6D"/> is cold.  Even as it is, if West has the 
<spade card="A"/>, 6D is cold, making
the slam close to 50%.  There is even some chance that we could miss
an excellent grand slam.  Since partner is well shy of his opening
bid, and slam is still 50%, I'd have to say I bid my hand timidly.
</p>
</body>
</article>
