<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge"
         xmlns:call="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge#call"
>
<title>An Early Squeeze</title>
<body>
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="KQ83" he="K653" di="3" cl="K832"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="JT96" he="QT92" di="KT95" cl="6"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="754" he="J8" di="AJ62" cl="JT97"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="A2" he="A74" di="Q874" cl="AQ54"/>
</diagram>
<auction dealer="S">
<call code="1NT"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="2C"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="2D"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="3N"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<!--
South   West    North   East
1NT     Pass    2C      Pass
2D      Pass    3NT     All pass
-->
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
West led the <spade card="J"/>, which declarer won in hand.  On a 3-2 club break,
this contract would be cold, but that was not to be today.
</p><p>
Still, declarer found a way to put West through the wringer, simply by
running the top clubs.  On the second club West could afford to pitch a heart.
On the third club, West began to sweat a little. 
He obviously could not pitch a spade or another heart, so he was forced
to pitch a diamond.  Declarer then exited with the fourth club at this
position:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="KQ8" he="K653" di="3" cl="^8"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="T96" he="QT9" di="KT9" cl=""/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="75" he="J8" di="AJ62" cl="^J"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="2" he="A74" di="Q874" cl="^5"/>
</diagram>
West has to hold onto his major suit guards, so he again pitches
a diamond.  But now the opponents can only take two diamond tricks, so
declarer can safely take the time to set up his hearts.
</p><p>
So maybe the heart pitch wasn't so wise, after all.  What if West, instead,
simply discards two diamond on the first two clubs?  At the fourth club,
West again can't pitch a spade.  If he pitches a heart, we get the same
position as before, so West must pitch a <em>third</em> diamond.
</p><p>
Declarer wins East's heart exit in dummy and ducks a diamond to West's
stiff king.  West exits another heart, won in hand.
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="KQ8" he="65" di="" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="T96" he="QT" di="" cl=""/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="75" he="" di="AJ6" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="2" he="7" di="Q87" cl=""/>
</diagram>
Declarer, in hand, leads a low spade to dummy, forcing West to play
either the <spade card="9"/> or <spade card="T"/>.  Then declarer
exits the heart, and West is forced to concede a trick in spades.  The
defense gets two hearts, a diamond and a club.
</p>
</body>
</article>
