<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge"
         xmlns:call="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge#call"
>
<title>Restricted Choice</title>
<date>July 14, 1996</date>
<body>
<diagram>
<header>
<dealer>North</dealer>
<vul>Both</vul>
<scoring>Matchpoints</scoring>
<source href="http://www.okbridge.com/">OKbridge</source>
<!-- (IMP-28.7, 1995) -->
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="KT9" he="K98" di="K862" cl="QT9"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="732" he="62" di="A73" cl="J8742"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="QJ84" he="AT74" di="JT94" cl="6"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="A65" he="QJ53" di="Q5" cl="AK53"/>
</diagram>
<auction dealer="N">
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="1N"/>
<call code="P"/>

<call code="3N"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<call code="P"/>
<!--
North   East    South   West
Pass    Pass    1NT     Pass    
3NT     All pass
-->
</auction>
<hr/>
<p>
Against <contract code="3N"/>, West led the <spade card="7"/>, which went to the 10,
jack, and ace.
</p><p>
Declarer then led a heart to the king and ace, and East exited with
the <diamond card="J"/>.   This was duck all around, and East continued with
a low diamond to the queen and West's ace.  West continued with his
last diamond, won in dummy, declarer pitching a spade from hand.
Declarer then cashed his two hearts and three rounds of clubs at this
position:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="KT" he="" di="8" cl="9"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="32" he="" di="" cl="J8"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="Q8" he="T" di="9" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="6" he="3" di="" cl="^K5"/>
</diagram>
</p><p>
Declarer has found nothing breaking.  Still, on the <club card="K"/>, East is
squeezed in three suits.  If he parts with the a spade, declarer gets two spade
tricks. If he parts with a diamond, dummy's diamond is good.  And if he
parts with a heart, declarer's heart is good.
</p><p>
This is a triple squeeze.  Note that the count has not been rectified.
</p><p>
Sadly, our declarer decided that West led the <spade card="7"/> from a doubleton,
and therefore thought the end position was:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="KT" he="" di="8" cl="9"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="3" he="" di="9" cl="J8"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="Q82" he="T" di="" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="6" he="3" di="" cl="^K5"/>
</diagram>
</p><p>
When East parted with a spade, declarer led his last heart, which declarer
hoped would force East to lead spades into the <spade cards="KT"/>.  As the cards were,
however, East cashed the <diamond card="9"/>, setting the contract.
</p><p>
Might West's spade lead be from a doubleton?  It certainly might, but
West is know to have started with only two hearts.  If he held two
small hearts and two small spades, and he chose to lead a major,
about half of the time he would lead a heart.  But with
three spades and two hearts, he will almost always choose the spade.
</p><p>
This is a subtle form of restricted choice, and I think it leads
to the conclusion that West is more likely to have started
with three spades.
</p><p>
The spade lead was the only one with a chance to set this contract.
All other leads give declarer his ninth trick.
</p></body>
</article>
