<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>A Slow Coup</title>
<body>
<diagram id="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="98" he="AK7" di="A985432" cl="2"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="K752" he="94" di="KQJ7" cl="Q98"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="T64" he="Q8532" di="6" cl="JT64"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AQJ3" he="JT6" di="T" cl="AK753"/>
<!--
             S: 98
             H: AK7
             D: A985432
             C: 2

S: K752                    S: T64          
H: 94                      H: Q8532        
D: KQJ7                    D: 6            
C: Q98                     C: JT64         

             S: AQJ3
             H: JT6
             D: T
             C: AK753
-->
</diagram>
<p>
Can North/South make any game?
</p><p>
In <contract code="5D"/>, the defense gets three trumps.
</p><p>
Can <contract code="3N"/> make?  It's hard to see how without a little help
from the defense. Declarer has six top tricks, with a two more which can set
be up in spades and one more in clubs, or, even more slowly, in his long
diamond suit.  Timing is difficult, however.  For example, on a
club lead, one entry to the South hand is lost, and when declarer
leads a spade from North, East covers with the ten, which blocks the
spade suit.
</p><p>
What about <contract code="4S"/>?  On a trump lead, win the queen, cash
the minor winners, cross with a heart to dummy, then ruff a diamond
(overruffing East if necessary), ruff a club, and ruff (or overruff)
another diamond.  East's best defense is to attempt to keep you from
scoring your small trump, so he should ruff ahead of you at each
opportunity, so the end position becomes:
<diagram original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="A" di="9854" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="K75" he="4" di="K" cl=""/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="" he="Q853" di="" cl="J"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="3" he="JT" di="" cl="73"/>
</diagram>
<!--
             S: -
             H: A
             D: 9854
             C: -

S: K75                     S: -
H: 4                       H: Q853
D: K                       D: -
C: -                       C: J        

             S: 3
             H: JT
             D: -
             C: 73
-->
Note, you've ruffed once with your ace.
</p><p>
The <heart card="A"/> is still available for one more diamond lead off dummy,
and you finally get to ruff with your three, East out of trumps.
</p><p>
You score all four trumps in the South hand, a club ruff in North,
and five top tricks in the other suits.  Amusingly, the three
defensive tricks are West's remaining trumps.
</p><p>
I believe this extended effort to score the trump three is what
Kelsey and Ottlik call an "elopement" play.
</p>
</body>
</article>
