<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>A Double Strip</title>
<body>
<diagram id="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="92" he="964" di="AK97" cl="AJ63"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="T853" he="QJ7" di="Q82" cl="QT5"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="AQ6" he="KT852" di="T64" cl="97"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="KJ74" he="A3" di="J53" cl="K842"/>
</diagram>
<!--
             S: 92
             H: 964
             D: AK97
             C: AJ63

S: T853                    S: AQ6          
H: QJ7                     H: KT852        
D: Q82                     D: T64          
C: QT5                     C: 97           

             S: KJ74
             H: A3
             D: J53
             C: K842
-->
<p>
Can North/South make any game?
</p><p>
North/South cannot make <contract code="3N"/> on heart leads.
Does <contract code="5C"/> or <contract code="5D"/> make?  No - 
there is no way for declarer to avoid losing a diamond, a heart, and a spade.
</p><p>
No, the only game which can make (double dummy) is <contract code="4S"/>.
</p><p>
Suppose West leads a heart.  Declarer ducks the first heart, wins the
second, and crosses with a diamond to lead a spade.  East plays low,
and declarer plays the jack, West following low.  A club to the
jack, and another spade off dummy.  This time, East should win,
and continue hearts, declarer ruffs leading to this position:
<diagram original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="" di="K97" cl="A63"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="T8" he="" di="Q8" cl="QT"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="Q" he="T5" di="T6" cl="9"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="K" he="" di="J5" cl="K84"/>
</diagram>
<!--
             S: -
             H: -
             D: K97
             C: A63

S: T8                      S: Q
H: -                       H: T5
D: Q8                      D: T6
C: QT                      C: 9

             S: K
             H: -
             D: J5
             C: K84
-->
</p><p>
Declarer draws East's last trump, pitching a club from dummy, then runs
his clubs, West getting caught on the last club:
<diagram original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="" di="K9^7" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="T" he="" di="Q8" cl=""/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="" he="^T" di="T6" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="" di="J5" cl="^8"/>
</diagram>
<!--
             S: -
             H: -
             D: K9*7*
             C: -

S: T                       S: -
H: -                       H: *T*
D: Q8                      D: T6
C: -                       C: -

             S: -
             H: -
             D: J5
             C: *8*
-->
If West ruffs, he is endplayed, and if he pitches, he only gets
his spade trick.</p>
<p>  This is fundamentally the same end position as
in our first example.
The difference here is that declarer's trump suit was bad enough that
West always had a natural trump trick, so maybe it was wrong to force
declarer to ruff a heart?  What if, instead, the defense adopts a
passive defense, leading clubs at every opportunity?
</p><p>
Declarer wins the first club in dummy, and leads a spade.
East ducks, declarer wins the jack, and crosses with a diamond
and leads another spade.
</p><p>
East flies the ace and continues clubs.  Declarer wins in hand,
cashes the spade king, and exits a spade to West.
</p><p>
West can safely exit in hearts or clubs.  Declarer wins and runs
all his non-diamond winners.  On the last club, the situation is:
<diagram original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="9" di="K9" cl="^3"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="" he="QJ" di="Q8" cl=""/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="" he="KT" di="T6" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="3" di="J5" cl="^8"/>
</diagram>
<!--
             S: -
             H: 9
             D: K9
             C: *3*

S: -                       S: -
H: QJ                      H: KT
D: Q8                      D: T6
C: -                       C: -

             S: -
             H: 3
             D: J5
             C: *8*
-->
West cannot pitch a diamond, so he must pitch a heart.
</p><p>
Likewise, East cannot pitch a diamond (or declarer can pin the ten by
leading the jack.)  So East must pitch a heart.  Now declarer exits
in hearts and the defense is forced to break the diamond suit, giving
declarer an extra trick in the suit.
</p><p>
In fact, declarer can engineer one of these two end-positions whatever
the defenders do.
</p><p>
<em>[ Special thanks to David DesJardin, for this analysis, and
Richard Pavlicek for pointing out that my original analysis
was wrong. ]</em>
</p>
</body>
</article>