<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>What Law?</title>
<body>
<diagram id="start">
<header>
<vul>E-W</vul>
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="T92" he="983" di="KQ864" cl="63"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="7" he="Q" di="AT97532" cl="A974"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="KQJ543" he="KJT52" di="" cl="52"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="A86" he="A764" di="J" cl="KQJT8"/>
</diagram>
<!--
East/West vulnerable

             S: T92
             H: 983
             D: KQ864
             C: 63

S: 7                       S: KQJ543
H: Q                       H: KJT52
D: AT97532                 D:
C: A974                    C: 52

             S: A86
             H: A764
             D: J
             C: KQJT8
-->
<p>
East/West can make <contract code="5S"/>, losing just the major aces (pitching
a club on the diamond ace.)
</p><p>
North/South can only make six tricks in clubs - four clubs and two aces -
but that's not the limit of the hand.  Would you believe North/South
can make nine tricks in diamonds, with the 7-0 split?
</p><p>
Say West leads a major.  Which is irrelevant, so say spades.  Declarer wins,
and leads high clubs, West ducks one round and wins the second round. 
West leads a heart, again won in the South hand, and two clubs are run,
pitching hearts from North, leading to:
<diagram original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="T9" he="" di="KQ864" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  di="AT97532"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="86" he="764" di="J" cl="9"/>
</diagram>
<!--
             S: T9
             H:  - 
             D: KQ864
             C:  - 

S:  -             
H:  -            
D: AT97532      
C:  -          

             S: 86
             H: 764
             D: J
             C: 8
-->
East's hand is irrelevant, with West holding all trumps.
</p><p>
A heart is led from South, and West must ruff, but how high?  It's a losing
proposition to ruff with the ace.  A ruff with the ten is overruffed, and
North exits a spade, West forced to ruff.  West is on lead at:
<diagram original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="T" he="" di="K864" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  di="A9753"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="8" he="76" di="J" cl="8"/>
</diagram>
<!--
             S: T
             H:  - 
             D: K864
             C:  - 

S:  -                    
H:  -                   
D: A9753               
C:  -                 

             S: 8
             H: 76
             D: J
             C: 8
-->
West can cash the <diamond card="A"/> and exit a diamond, but dummy finesses
the diamond, and exits again in spades, and West is forced again to lead
from his diamond suit.
</p><p>
West could lead diamonds earlier, but there is no way for him to
prevent declarer from scoring four diamonds along with three clubs and
the two major aces.
</p><p>
That's nine tricks, if you're still with me, making the <contract code="6D"/>
sacrifice a winner. Since East/West make 11 tricks in their seven-card
spade suit, and North/South make nine tricks in their six-card diamond
suit, that's 20 total tricks on a hand with 13 total trumps.
</p>
</body>
</article>
