<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>Blockage</title>
<body>
<diagram id="original">
<header>
<vul>E-W</vul>
</header>
<hand seat="N" sp="964" he="93" di="T72" cl="AKT93"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="85" he="AQ54" di="QJ63" cl="Q76"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="AQJ" he="KJ7" di="A84" cl="8542"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="KT732" he="T862" di="K95" cl="J"/>
</diagram>
<!--
E/W Vulnerable

             S: 964
             H: 93
             D: T72
             C: AKT93

S: 85                      S: AQJ
H: AQ54                    H: KJ7
D: QJ63                    D: A84
C: Q76                     C: 8542

             S: KT732
             H: T862
             D: K95
             C: J
-->
<p>
East/West can make <contract code="3N"/> from either side, because there is no way
for the defense to untangle the club suit.  North's lack of entries
is the flaw.  Declarer can lose a trick in diamonds, a trick
in spades, and two top clubs, but has nine trick after.  If the club
ten and jack were switched, <contract code="3NT"/> would go down.
</p><p>
So perhaps, at favorable vulnerability, North/South should sacrifice
in <contract code="4S"/>?  The defense starts with two spades.  Declarer wins the second, but
has no time to set up a heart ruff.  Declarer gets only one pitch on
the clubs, due to the blockage, so must still lose five tricks in the
red suits as well as two spades, for down four, -800.
</p><p>
If North/South play the contract in clubs, however, the blockage is no
problem.  The defense attacks hearts, forcing a ruff, and North leads a
diamond.  East wins, but can't continue hearts, so he exits a diamond, won with
the king.  The <club card="J"/> is led, ducked all around, leading to this
position:
<diagram original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="964" he="" di="T" cl="AKT"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="85" he="A" di="QJ" cl="Q7"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="AQJ" he="" di="8" cl="854"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="KT732" he="T" di="5" cl=""/>
</diagram>
<!--
             S: 964
             H: -  
             D: T
             C: AKT

S: 85                      S: AQJ
H: A                       H: -  
D: QJ                      D: 8
C: Q7                      C: 854

             S: KT732
             H: T
             D: 5
             C: -  
-->
A diamond is led, and West wins.  If West leads a red suit
winner, declare ruffs, and East pitches a spade.  Declarer then runs
two rounds of clubs, and then leads a spade.  Eventually, North/South
score five clubs, and the diamond and spade kings.
</p><p>
This lack of entries is one of the most common reason that a six-card fit is
better for a sacrifice.
</p>
</body>
</article>
