<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>A Variation</title>
<body>
<diagram id="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="8" he="AK984" di="AT8" cl="QJ43"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="632" he="T3" di="7542" cl="KT87"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="QJ75" he="Q652" di="J63" cl="52"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AKT94" he="J7" di="KQ9" cl="A96"/>
</diagram>
<!--
             S: 8
             H: AK984
             D: AT8
             C: QJ43

S: 632                     S: QJ75
H: T3                      H: Q652
D: 7542                    D: J63
C: KT87                    C: 52

             S: AKT94
             H: J7
             D: KQ9
             C: A96
-->
<p>
Declarer starts with a mere eight top tricks, but has many prospects
for more in hearts, spades, and clubs.
In notrump, declarer can set up two tricks in any of these suits, but
must lose a trick in the suit in order to do so.  In order to get twelve
tricks, then, declarer must lose two tricks.  That's not going to be a
successful approach to twelve tricks.
</p>
<p>
In hearts, declarer has an inevitable heart loser and an inevitable club
loser.
</p><p>
In clubs, declarer can't ruff out the hearts or spades without setting up
another trump trick for West.
</p><p>
The spade contract, however, is another matter.  If South declares
<contract code="6S"/>, the contract can be made.  
</p><p>
Suppose West leads a diamond (the safest defense.) South wins in hand,
crosses to the <heart card="A"/>, and leads the stiff spade off dummy.
East split his honors, declarer wins the <spade cards="AK"/> and exits with
the <spade card="T"/>, leading to this position:
<diagram original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="K984" di="AT" cl="QJ"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="" he="T" di="754" cl="KT87"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="7" he="Q65" di="J6" cl="52"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="94" he="J" di="Q9" cl="A96"/>
</diagram>
<!--
             S:  - 
             H: K984
             D: AT
             C: QJ

S:  -                      S: 7
H: T                       H: Q65
D: 754                     D: J6
C: KT87                    C: 52

             S: 94
             H: J
             D: Q9
             C: A96
-->
If East exits in a minor, South wins in hand, draws the last trump,
and takes the ruffing finesse against East in hearts.
</p><p>
But what if East leads a low heart?  At first, that seems to kill an
entry, but that's an illusion. Since East holds the last trump,
declarer can afford to win the king, and take the ruffing finesse
immediately.
</p>
</body>
</article>
