<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge"
         xmlns:contract="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge#contract"
>
<title>The Miracle Combination</title>
<body>
<diagram id="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="AKQ963" he="A5" di="Q3" cl="JT2"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="872" he="K973" di="K987" cl="AQ"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="JT4" he="QT84" di="J54" cl="964"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="5" he="J62" di="AT62" cl="K8753"/>
</diagram>
<p>
This is the only example of a single suit responsible for
a double asymmetry.  The heart suit in isolation:
<diagram id="hearts">
<hand seat="N" he="A5"/>
<hand seat="W"  he="K973"/>
<hand seat="E"  he="QT84"/>
<hand seat="S" he="J62"/>
</diagram>
does not even appear to provide a one-way guard, much
less a more complicated two-way guard, but we'll find that
the only way to set <contract code="4S"/> is by a heart lead from
West, while the only way to set <contract code="3N"/> is by a heart
lead from East.
</p>
<h2>Spades</h2>
<p>
It would appear, at first, that East could set a <contract code="4S"/>
contract with a diamond lead.  Declarer plays a low diamond, West wins
the <diamond card="K"/> and exits a heart.
</p><p>
Declarer can win and draw trumps, but cannot untangle the diamond suit to
pitch his heart.
</p><p>
The solution is for declarer to play low from dummy on the first
diamond and unblock the <diamond card="Q"/> when West wins the king.
After winning the heart switch, declarer can draw trumps and finesse
against East's <diamond card="J"/>, then pitch the heart loser on the
<diamond card="A"/>.
</p><p>
What if East leads a heart?  Then declarer cannot avoid losing
a heart, but can keep East off lead long enough to set up his
clubs to pitch his diamond loser.
</p><p>
For example, if East leads a low heart, declarer covers it with
the jack and ducks the trick when West covers with the king.
East then can never get in to lead diamonds.
</p><p>
If East leads the <heart card="Q"/>, declarer wins this trick, and,
with the <heart card="J"/> in dummy, ensures that East cannot get
back in lead via the heart suit to lead diamonds.
</p><p>
If South declares <contract code="4S"/>, a low heart lead holds him to
nine tricks. South cannot avoid letting East win a heart trick, and
then lead  a diamond.  He must eventually lose a diamond, a heart and
two clubs.
</p><p>
Here the nature of the heart guard is not to provide a stopper or 
a trick, but to keep one opponent off lead.  A "non-material" guard, to
use the terminology of Kelsey and Ottlik's <em>Adventures in Card Play.</em>
</p>
<h2>Notrump</h2>
<p>East/West have to get active against <contract code="3N"/>, leading
hearts. The notrump contract starts with eight top tricks.  A ninth
might be set up by leading the diamond queen to West's king
and eventually finessing against East's diamond jack.
</p><p>
If South declares, and West leads a heart, declarer ducks and East
wins the <heart card="Q"/>.  Suppose East continues hearts.  Declarer
wins and runs his spades. ending in this position:
<diagram original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="^3" he="" di="Q3" cl="JT2"/>
<hand seat="W" sp="" he="K9" di="K9" cl="AQ"/>
<hand seat="E" sp="" he="T8" di="J5^4" cl="9"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="J" di="AT" cl="K8^7"/>
</diagram>
On the last spade, West can't pitch a diamond.  If he pitches a heart
he can be endplayed in clubs, getting two clubs and a heart
but forced to give up in diamonds in the end. 
</p><p>
So he must pitch the <club card="Q"/>.
But now declare plays a low club to the king, and West wins.
East/West get two more heart tricks, but declarer has the rest - the
<diamond card="A"/> and a club.
</p><p>
East cannot profit by shifting to a diamond or a club, either.
The diamond lead just sets up declarer's ninth trick, and the club
lead reduces to almost the same ending as above, only with one
fewer club for everybody.  Again West is squeezed.
</p><p>
West might lead the <heart card="K"/> but then declarer can set up
his ninth trick in hearts!
</p><p>
If North declares, though, East can defeat the contract with a
low heart lead.  However declarer twists and turns, East will
remain with the heart queen at the above end position, which means
West can pitch down to a single small heart.
</p><p>
So now the heart suit is a guard from the other direction, and
again it is a non-material guard.  This time, it forces West to
hold the <heart card="K"/> at the six-card end-position, and
therefore causes him to be squeezed in three suits.
</p><p>
This heart suit is magic.  Not only would you not believe that
it provides a guard at all giving the placement of the cards, but
it provides a guard in two opposite directions, one in a suit
contract, one in notrump, on exactly the same deal!
</p>
<h2>Clubs</h2>
<p>
It seems almost anti-climactic to note the pedestrian one-sided guard
provided by diamonds in a club contract.
</p><p>
If South declares <contract code="5C"/>, he cannot be harmed.  On a
heart lead, he wins and pitches two hearts on spades before attacking
clubs. Only West can get in, and he cannot profitably lead diamonds. 
The third round of clubs provides entry to dummy's spade for
South to pitch his diamond losers.
</p><p>
If North declares <contract code="5C"/>, a simply diamond lead by East
will set declarer. Declarer obviously cannot avoid two club losers,
and if he tries to run four spade tricks to pitch three diamonds, East
can ruff, giving the defense either a third club trick or a trick in
diamonds. 
</p>
<h2>Post-mortem</h2>
<p>
Here is the heart suit again:
<diagram src="#hearts"/>
The biggest advantage for the offense is that West is holding almost all
of the values.  The heart suit acts to protect declarer's advantage
in two different ways, depending in the contract.
</p><p>
In the notrump contract, it serves to ensure that West holds the heart
honor at the end position.  It can only do that if West is on opening
lead.
</p><p>
In the spade contract, the heart suit denies East a later entry
when declared by North.  Declarer can ensure that any heart
lost will be lost to West.  For timing reason, the
defense must get their heart trick before attacking diamonds,
but diamonds can only be profitably attacked by East.
So the heart suit here works in conjunction with the more traditional
diamond suit guard.
</p><p>
In five clubs, that diamond guard carries the full weight of the
contract.  It seems perverse that the non-material heart guard
is necessary to make nine tricks in notrump or ten tricks in spades,
but that the diamond guard alone is all that is needed to ensure
eleven tricks in clubs.
</p>
</body>
</article>
