<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge"
         xmlns:contract="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge#contract"
>
<title>Trashing Entries</title>
<body>
<diagram id="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="Q954" he="AQJ73" di="63" cl="AQ"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="K86" he="9542" di="AJ" cl="9752"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="JT73" he="K86" di="T4" cl="KT43"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="A2" he="T" di="KQ98752" cl="J86"/>
</diagram>
<p>
This is our first Double Asymmetry where immediate shortness
and ruffing does not obviously contribute to some of the asymmetry.
</p>
<h2>Three Notrump, by North</h2>
<p>
North, declaring <contract code="3N"/>, cannot make against best defense.
East leads a low spade, and declarer ducks.  West wins the king and
continues spades.  This puts North in a quandary - he has lost his
only entry to dummy before the diamonds are set up.
</p><p>
Still, he has what appears to be two club tricks, two spade tricks,
four heart tricks, and a diamond, if he can get them in time.
</p><p>
So declarer leads the <heart card="T"/>, finessing, and East ducks.
</p><p>
Declarer then finesses in clubs, and East wins.  At this position:
<diagram original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="Q9" he="AQJ7" di="63" cl="A"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="8" he="954" di="AJ" cl="975"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="JT" he="K8" di="T4" cl="T43"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="" di="KQ98752" cl="J8"/>
</diagram>
East can set declarer by leading a spade; the defense eventually getting
a total of two spades, a club, a heart, and a diamond.
</p>
<h2> Three Notrump, by South </h2>
<p>
The spade lead from East served two functions - first, it
killed South's entry to the long diamonds, and second, it did so
without providing declarer a second entry to North's hand.
</p><p>
If South declares, on the other hand, West can kill the diamond suit
by leading the <spade card="K"/>, but this give South two things in return.
The first is the immediate tempo advantage of having his second spade
trick set up right away. The second is that the spade suit
provides an interesting threat to East at the end position.
</p><p>
After the <spade card="K"/> lead, South wins the <spade card="A"/>,
and the play proceeds much as above.  Declarer leads the <heart card="T"/>,
ducked all around. Declarer then takes the club finesse.  East wins at
this position:
<diagram original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="Q95" he="AQJ7" di="63" cl="A"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="86" he="954" di="AJ" cl="975"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="JT7" he="K8" di="T4" cl="T43"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="2" he="" di="KQ98752" cl="J8"/>
</diagram>
</p>
<p>
East naturally leads the <spade card="J"/>, West unblocks the eight and
declarer's queen wins.  Declarer then unblocks the <club card="A"/>, and leads
a diamond to the king.  West must duck the first diamond.  If he wins
and shifts to spades, his side gets two spades, the <diamond card="A"/>,
and the <club card="K"/>, but then the diamonds are good.
</p><p>
Declarer then strands himself completely by continuing diamonds.
West wins at this position:
<diagram  original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="95" he="AQJ7" di="" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="6" he="954" di="" cl="97"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="T7" he="K8" di="" cl="T4"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="" di="Q9875" cl="J"/>
</diagram>
</p>
<p>West obviously cannot lead a club, or South's hand is good.</p>
<p>If West leads a spade, East gets his two spade tricks, but then must surrender the rest of the tricks by leading a heart (setting up North) or a club
(to the good South hand.)</p>
<p>If West leads a heart, South hops up with the <heart card="A"/>
and continues hearts, and again East is thrown in, this time with the
<spade card="9"/> a threat in dummy.</p>
<p>Whatever West leads, his side can only get two more tricks.</p>
<p>Perhaps East should not have exited a spade when in with the 
<club card="K"/>? It does not matter;  declarer can reach a
substantially similar end-position:
<diagram  original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="Q95" he="AQJ7" di="" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="86" he="954" di="" cl="97"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="JT7" he="K8" di="" cl="T4"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="2" he="" di="Q9875" cl="J"/>
</diagram>
West again on lead with the <diamond card="A"/>, and again the
defense cannot take more than two tricks.  This time, if West leads a
heart, declarer wins the ace, exits a heart, and then must duck the
first spade to finish the endplay.
</p><p>So, <contract code="3N"/> makes only if declared by South on
the above hand.</p> 
<h2> Five Diamonds, by South </h2>
<diagram copyid="start"/>
<p>
Now, what about the <contract code="5D"/> contract?
</p><p>
West leads a club, and the finesse is taken.  East continues a club.
Declarer then leads the <heart card="A"/> and <hear card="Q"/>,
forcing East to cover. Declarer ruffs low, and must ruff his good 
<club card="J"/> in dummy to pitch his spade loser on the 
<heart card="J"/>.  Declarer is now at this position:
<diagram  original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="Q954" he="73" di="6" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="K86" he="9" di="AJ" cl="9"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="JT73" he="" di="T4" cl="T"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="A" he="" di="KQ9875" cl=""/>
</diagram>
Declarer cannot avoid a second diamond loser.  If he leads a
diamond to the king, West wins the ace and continues with the
<heart card="9"/>.  East ruffs with the <diamond card="T"/>,
and West's <diamond card="J"/> is promoted.
</p>
<p>The attack of the club suit killed a vital entry.  Without that
lead, declarer could afford to pitch the spade loser after the trumps
are drawn.
</p>
<h2>Five Diamonds, by North</h2>
<p>So maybe <contract code="5D"/> can make if North declares?  Indeed,
it can.  It may appear that East can lead a spade to set the contract,
but that is an illusion.</p>
<p>North calls for the <spade card="A"/>, then plays the 
<heart card="A"/> and <heart card="Q"/> immediately.
East must cover, and declarer ruffs.  Declarer then leads
the <diamond card="K"/>, West winning at this position:
<diagram  original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="Q95" he="J73" di="6" cl="AQ"/>
<hand seat="W" sp="K8" he="95" di="J" cl="9752"/>
<hand seat="E" sp="JT7" he="8" di="T" cl="KT43"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="2" he="" di="Q9875" cl="J86"/>
</diagram>
</p><p>
West is caught in something like "Morton's Fork."  If he cashes
the <spade card="K"/>, declarer can pitch two clubs on major-suit
winners in hand. And if West does not cash the <spade card="K"/>,
the spade winner vanished on the <heart card="J"/>.  In either case,
declarer is able to get rid of one of his black suit losers.
</p>
<h2>Post-mortem</h2>
<p>
This is a rather astounding deal.
<ul>
<li>    <contract code="3N"/> <em>fails</em> declared by North because a vital spade entry can be
        killed immediately.</li>

<li>    <contract code="3N"/> <em>makes</em> declared by South because
        the cost of killing the spade entry is too high, leading to a
        stunning endplay, with declarer deliberately destroying all of
        his entries.</li>

<li>    <contract code="5D"/> <em>fails</em> declared by South,
        because a natural club entry is killed, forcing South to ruff
        a winner to pitch a loser, which in turn forces South to delay
        pulling trumps until after pitching is loser, which lets
        East/West score a second trump on a trump promotion.</li>

<li>    <contract code="5D"/> <em>makes</em> declared by North,
	because the club entry is preserved, allowing North to
	lead trumps.  West is caught in a Morton's Fork, having to
	choose which black suit loser he wants to let declarer
	pitch.</li> 
</ul>
</p>
<p>
Okay, I warned you these would be complicated.</p>
<p>
The two black suit holdings are providing subtle protection, even though
they look like traditional guards.  In both cases, the ace of the
suit is providing a vital entry, and in both cases, that entry can
be knocked out safely from only one side.
</p>
</body>
</article>
