<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>Blockage</title>
<body>
<diagram id="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="T3" he="AKJ764" di="Q64" cl="KQ"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="Q875" he="92" di="JT9" cl="AJ76"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="92" he="QT53" di="A875" cl="983"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AKJ64" he="8" di="K32" cl="T542"/>
</diagram>
<p>
This is the first part-score deal of this collection.  Of course, given
the North/South hands, nobody will end up in a part-score, but no game
makes, double dummy.
</p>
<h2>Hearts</h2>
<p>
In the unlikely event that South is declarer in hearts, South can only
make eight tricks on a diamond lead.  There is no time to find a discard
for the second diamond loser, and it is impossible to avoid two trump
losers, two diamond losers, and a club loser.
</p><p>
However, when declared by North, West only gets to lead diamonds once,
when in with the <club card="A"/>.  Declarer can eliminate clubs and
spades from East's hand then throw East in with trumps to give up a
second diamond trick at the end.
</p>
<h2> Spades </h2>
<p>
In the unlikely event that North declares a spade contract, he can
take at most eight tricks.  East leads a spade on opening lead,
and when West gets in with the <club card="A"/>, West also leads a
spade. This kills declarer's chance to ruff a club in dummy, and the
North is left with four spade tricks, two hearts, a diamond, and a
club. 
</p><p>
With South declaring spades, West might try a diamond lead.  East
has to duck or he gives declarer a second diamond trick, and South
wins the <diamond card="K"/> in hand.
</p><p>
South cannot afford to try to set up the club ruff immediate.  Instead,
he takes the top hearts, pitching a diamond from hand, and then leads the
<club card="K"/> at this position:
<diagram original="start" id="next">
<hand seat="N" sp="T3" he="J764" di="Q6" cl="^KQ"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="Q875" he="" di="T9" cl="AJ76"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="92" he="QT" di="A87" cl="9^83"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AKJ64" he="" di="3" cl="T54^2"/>
</diagram>
Should West win the first club?  If he wins it, what suit does he
exit in?</p>
<p>
If West exits a trump, declarer wins in dummy, cashes the second
club and exits a <em>low</em> diamond from dummy.
</p><p>
If East does not fly the <diamond card="A"/>, West must win.
Caught on lead at this position:
<diagram original="next">
<hand seat="N" sp="3" he="J764" di="Q" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="Q87" he="" di="T" cl="J7"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="9" he="QT" di="A8" cl="9"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AKJ6" he="" di="" cl="T5"/>
</diagram>
West can't lead a club. A diamond lead gives declare an entry for
a club ruff.  And a spade lead gives declarer an extra spade trick.
West cannot avoid letting declarer make four of the six remaining
tricks.
</p><p>
So maybe East should have flown the <diamond card="A"/> when the low diamond
was led off dummy?  After all, while this sets up the <diamond card="Q"/>,
there is no remaining entry to use it.
</p><p>
But what does East exit with after flying the <diamond card="A"/>?
<diagram original="next">
<hand seat="N" sp="3" he="J764" di="Q" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W" sp="Q87" he="" di="T" cl="J7"/>
<hand seat="E" sp="9" he="QT" di="87" cl="9"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="AKJ6" he="" di="" cl="T5"/>
</diagram>
</p><p>
If East leads a trump, declarer cashes two top trumps then throws
West in with a third trump.  West can cash the <club card="J"/>, but then
must give declare a minor suit winner, either the <club card="T"/> in hand
or the <diamond card="Q"/> in dummy.  If East leads the 
<heart card="Q"/> declarer ruffs high, ruffs the club, then leads the
good <diamond card="Q"/> off dummy,  pitching his last club.  West
can ruff it (if he pitched his diamond) or not.  Either way, he is
endplayed into leading to declarers <spade cards="KJ"/>
in the end-position.
</p><p>
So, let's step back one more step, to when West won the first club
and exited a trump.
<diagram src="#next"/>
<!--
             S: T3
             H: J764
             D: Q6
             C: *K*Q

S: Q875                 S: 92
H: -                    H: QT
D: T9                   D: A87
C: AJ76                 C: 9*8*3

             S: AKJ64
             H: -
             D: 3
             C: T54*2*
-->
What if, after winning the club, he exits a club?  Declarer wins
in dummy and leads a low diamond.  If West wins, he is again
stuck, so East must fly the <diamond card="A"/>, as before.  But here
the <spade card="T"/> remains in dummy as a potential entry to that
good diamond, giving declarer his ninth trick again.
</p><p>
Lastly, what happens if West exits a diamond?  Declarer plays low,
and the blockage in diamonds has its affect again.  East can overtake,
but has no satisfying shift, while if West is left on lead, he
cannot prevent declarer from ruffing a club in dummy.
</p><p>
West also cannot profit from holding up the club one round - the blockage
in diamonds is firmly around his neck.
</p>
<p>The diamond suit blockage here is crucial.  It does not keep the defense
from taking the two diamond tricks which are rightfully theirs, but it
does allow South to dictate who takes the second diamond trick, and, since
the <diamond card="A"/> is East's only entry, it gives declarer the
tempo to set up a club ruff.
</p>
</body>
</article>
