<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>Untitle IV</title>
<!--
#
# GIB Input
#
n A62.KQ982.765.J2
e 54.A73.KJT94.863
s 973.J.A832.KQ974
w KQJT8.T654.Q.AT5
#
# iDeal Input
#
North A62 KQ982 765 J2
East 54 A73 KJT94 863
South 973 J A832 KQ974
West KQJT8 T654 Q AT5
-->
<!-- level 2 - hearts, diamonds -->
<body>
<diagram id="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="A62" he="KQ982" di="765" cl="J2"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="KQJT8" he="T654" di="Q" cl="AT5"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="54" he="A73" di="KJT94" cl="863"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="973" he="J" di="A832" cl="KQ974"/>
</diagram>
<h2>Notrump</h2>
<p>If East/West declare notrump, the defense starts with 
a heart.  If East ducks the heart, North/South set up
four clubs, and have a heart, a spade, a diamond and four
clubs.  So East must win.
</p><p>
Attacking diamonds is useless, because East has no entry -
South just wins the first diamond and sets up clubs.
</p><p>
So East must attack spades.  North wins the first spade,
takes a high heart, then attacks clubs.
West can win and take four spades, but those are his last
tricks.  North/South get a spade, a heart, a diamond and
four clubs.
</p>
<p>If North/South declare notrump, the defense is much
the same, with the suits reversed - East/West attack
diamonds, and South must win, or East/West shift to
spades, setting up four spade tricks, plus a trick in
each suit.
</p><p>
If South attacks clubs, West wins the second, then shifts
to the <spade card="K"/>.  If North ducks, West leads
a heart to East's ace and East takes four diamonds for
a total of seven tricks.  So North must win the spade, but
now is stuck with no entry to the good clubs, and the heart
suit un-established.
</p><p>
So, after winning the first trick, South could lead only
one club, then shift to hearts.  East wins, cashes
one diamond (West pitching a club) and exits a spade:
<diagram original="start">
<hand seat="N" sp="A62" he="KQ98" di="6" cl="2"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="^KQJT8" he="T65" di="" cl="A"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="^54" he="73" di="JT9" cl="86"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="97^3" he="" di="83" cl="KQ97"/>
</diagram>
If North ducks or wins, it doesn't matter, he has only
two heart tricks along with his earlier diamond ace
and club.
</p>
<h2>Spades</h2>
<p>If North/South declare spades, East/West start with
spades until North wins.  The best North can do is win
the second spade.
</p>
<h2>Hearts</h2>
<h2>Diamonds</h2>
<h2>Clubs</h2>
</body>
</article>
