<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>A Subtle Promotion</title>
<!--
s AK.A8742.T84.T72
e 832.QT3.AKQ72.96
s JT954.KJ.J95.K43
w Q76.965.63.AQJ85
-->
<!-- level 2 - diamonds, clubs -->
<body>
<diagram id="base">
<hand seat="N" sp="AK" he="A8742" di="T84" cl="T72"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="Q76" he="965" di="63" cl="AQJ85"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="832" he="QT3" di="AKQ72" cl="96"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="JT954" he="KJ" di="J95" cl="K43"/>
</diagram>
<h2>Notrump</h2>
<p>
In notrump, each side can run at least seven top tricks. East/West can
take 10 tricks by leading a diamond to the ace, club finesse, run four
diamonds, then finesse clubs again and run clubs.  North/South get seven
tricks by leading a spade to the king, heart finesse, heart king, another
spade, and then running three good hearts.
</p>
<h2>Spades</h2>
<p>
Against a spade contract, East/West must get a spade, so they simply
take their six top tricks in the minors.
</p>
<h2>Hearts</h2>
<p>
Against a heart contract, East/West start the same way - diamond, club
finesse, two diamonds, club finesse, club ace, then a fourth club.  East
ruffs high with the queen (or 10) and this promotes West's <heart card="9"/>.
</p>
<h2>Diamonds</h2>
<p>
If East/West declare in diamonds, the defense takes two top spades, finesses
in hearts, cashes the <heart card="K"/>, ruffs a spade, cashes the <heart card="A"/>,
and finishes up with a fourth round of hearts, promoting South's <diamond card="J"/>.
</p>
<h2>Clubs</h2><p>
The trickiest case is when East/West declare clubs.
</p><p>
North/South take their two spades, three hearts, and a spade ruff as before.
On the third round of hearts, South pitches a diamond, and, when North
leads a fourth round of hearts, South pitches a diamond again at this
position:
</p>
<diagram id="endposition" original="base">
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="^87" di="T84" cl="T7"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="" he="" di="AKQ72" cl="96"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="" he="" di="63" cl="AQJ85"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="JT" he="" di="J^9" cl="K42"/>
</diagram>
<p>
What should East/West do?  If they ruff in East, they can only finesse
once in trumps.  But if East pitches a diamond and ruff with the West
hand, they only have one entry to dummy, since South can ruff a
second diamond entry, so again they can only finesse in clubs once.
</p>
</body>
</article>
