<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>Repeated Promotion</title>
<!--
#
# GIB Input ( http://www.gibware.com/ )
#
n AKQT.T985.Q3.932
e J8653.64.9872.K6
s 9.J73.AKJ65.J754
w 742.AKQ2.T4.AQT8
#
# iDeal Input ( http://bridge.thomasoandrews.com/iDeal/notes.html )
#
north is {AKQT T985 Q3 932}
east is {J8653 64 9872 K6}
south is {9 J73 AKJ65 J754}
west is {742 AKQ2 T4 AQT8}
-->
<!-- level 1 - spades, hearts, clubs -->
<body>
<diagram id="base">
<hand seat="N" sp="AKQT" he="T985" di="Q3" cl="932"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="742" he="AKQ2" di="T4" cl="AQT8"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="J8653" he="64" di="9872" cl="K6"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="9" he="J73" di="AKJ65" cl="J754"/>
</diagram>

<h2>Notrump</h2>
<p>Against notrump, North/South have three top spades and five top
diamonds, while East/West have three hearts and four clubs (finessing
the jack.)</p> 
<h2>Spades</h2>
<p>If East/West are declaring spades, North/South take three top spades then
four top diamonds.</p>
<p>If North/South are declaring spades, the defense starts with three hearts,
and three clubs, East pitching two diamonds.  East gets at least one more
trick in trumps.</p>

<h2>Hearts</h2>
<p>If North/South declare hearts, East/West run three top heart, then the 
<club card="K"/> and a club back, finessing the jack, and two more clubs.
On the last club, if North ruffs, West's low trump is the outstanding trump.
If North fails to ruff, that's the defense's seventh trick.</p>
<p>If East/West declare hearts, North/South cash two diamonds then three
spades.  Finally, a fourth spade is ruffed high in South, promoting
a second trump trick for North/South.</p>
<h2>Diamonds</h2>
<p>If North/South declare diamonds, the defense starts with three hearts
and then four clubs.  On the fourth club, if North ruffs low, East
overruffs, while if North ruffs high, it promotes a trump trick for the
defense.</p>
<p>
If East/West declare diamonds, North/South draws trumps immediately,
taking three spades and five diamonds total.</p>
<h2>Clubs</h2>
<p>If North/South declare clubs, the defense simply draws trumps and takes its
three heart winners.</p>
<p>
If East/West declare clubs, North takes his three top spades, South pitching
two hearts, and then the defense plays off top diamonds until West ruffs.
</p>
<diagram original="base">
<hand seat="N" sp="T" he="T985" di="" cl="932"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="" he="AKQ2" di="" cl="AQT8"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="J8" he="64" di="98" cl="K6"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="J" di="^KJ6" cl="J754"/>
</diagram>
<p>
North/South have taken only five tricks.  East/West appear to have lots of
tricks - four clubs, three hearts, two spades.  Yet the third diamond crushes
them.
</p><p>If West doesn't ruff, another
diamond lead promotes a seventh trick for the defense.
</p><p>So West ruffs with the <club card="T"/>, promoting one long trump
in the South hand. Now West's timing is all crossed up.  If he draws
three rounds of trumps and then attacks hearts, South ruffs and cashes
more diamonds.  If West instead attacks hearts immediately, South
ruffs the second and continues diamonds, promoting a second trump
trick.</p>
<p>Whenever South gets in, he will be able to play another high diamond.
If West has any more trumps, the lead promotes another trump trick for
South, and if West has no more trumps, the diamonds are good.
</p>
<p>
This deal, in clubs at least, is not really a six-plus-promotion example,
but rather a five-plus-promotion example.
</p>
</body>
</article>
