<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>A First Example</title>
<!--
GIB Input
n KQT3.K963.975.J2
e 9852.JT.T632.Q65
w A64.AQ84.QJ.AT87
s J7.752.AK84.K943
-->
<!-- level 1 - spades -->
<body>
<diagram id="base">
<hand seat="N" sp="KQT3" he="K963" di="975" cl="J2"/>
<hand seat="W" sp="A64" he="AQ84" di="QJ" cl="AT87"/>
<hand seat="E" sp="9852" he="JT" di="T632" cl="Q65"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="J7" he="752" di="AK84" cl="K943"/>
</diagram>

<h2>Notrump</h2>
<p>If North/South declare notrump, the defense starts with hearts,
killing the entry to the North hand before the spades are established.
South gets one spade, one heart, three diamonds and, with care, a
club.
</p><p>If East/West declare notrump, the defense starts with spades, which
establishes three spade tricks before the heart entry to North is
killed.  North/South get three spades, a heart, two diamonds and
either another diamond or a club.
</p>
<h2>Spades</h2>
<p>
If East/West declare spades, the defense starts with trumps.  West
can duck the <spade card="A"/> as many times as he wants, he still
cannot get to East's hand before North gets in again to finish pulling
trumps. North/South get three spades, a heart, two diamonds, and an
eventual club.
</p><p>
If North/South declare spades, West leads a low heart and East gets
to ruff a heart when West wins the second round of trumps.
</p><p>
<h2>Hearts</h2>
If North/South declare hearts, a heart lead keeps them from scoring
any extra trumps, and they are left with three spades, one trump,
and two diamonds.
</p><p>
If East/West declare in hearts, the defenders start by attacking
spades while North still has a heart entry. When North gets in with
a heart, North runs spades and West is forced to overruff South on
the fourth round, and North gets another heart, for two spades, two
hearts two diamonds and, eventually, a club.
</p>
<h2>Diamonds</h2>
<p>
If declared by North/South, the defense starts with (low) heart leads.
This allows the defense to get two heart tricks and killing declarer's
entry to the long spades.  That means that North/South
loses a diamond, two hearts, a spade, two clubs and either a third
heart or, when South ruffs the third heart, a second diamond.
</p><p>
If declared by East/West, South takes two top diamonds before
attacking spades.  West wins the second one, and plays ace and a
heart, the king winning in dummy.   Another two spades are led,
pitching a heart and a club.  Then the club jack is led.  East has
to cover, South plays the king, and West wins the ace and is caught
in an endplay:
</p>
<diagram original="base">
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="96" di="9" cl="2"/>
<hand seat="W" sp="" he="Q8" di="" cl="T8"/>
<hand seat="E" sp="" he="" di="T6" cl="65"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="" di="84" cl="94"/>
</diagram>
<p>
There is no way to prevent North/South from scoring two tricks.
</p><p>
If West leads a high heart, and East pitches a club, South ruffs low and
exits in clubs to West's hand.  West, force to exit in clubs or hearts,
must allow South to ruff with the nine in dummy or eight in hand,
respectively, unless East ruffs high.  Either way, North/South must score
one of their two remaining trumps. Twist and turn as they might, East/West
can't keep North/South from scoring two more tricks, for two spades, the
heart king, two top diamonds and two more tricks.
</p>

<h2>Clubs</h2>
<p>If declared by East/West in clubs, the defense starts with spades.
Eventually, South gets to pitch a losing heart on a spade.  South then
takes two top diamonds and exits in diamonds to this situation:
</p>
<diagram original="base">
<hand seat="N" sp="K" he="96" di="" cl="J2"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="" he="Q" di="" cl="AT87"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="9" he="" di="6" cl="Q65"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="" di="8" cl="K943"/>
</diagram>
<p>
East, stuck on lead, can't avoid two more losers.  Say they lead a club
to the ace, and a club back to the jack, queen, and king.  South simply
continues with a high diamond, and West is forced to ruff and South scores
a long trump.
</p><p>
If declared by North/South, the defense starts with low hearts, which has
the usual entry-killing effect. North wins the first heart, then attacks
spades.  West wins the second spade, leads a low heart to East, who then
leads a club to West's ace and a club.  West cashes a heart and leads
a low club to the jack, queen and king.</p>
<diagram original="base">
<hand seat="N" sp="KQ" he="9" di="975" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="4" he="Q" di="QJ" cl="T8"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="9" he="" di="T632" cl="6"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="" di="AK84" cl="94"/>
</diagram>
<p>
East/West have taken two hearts, a spade and a club, and they will
get a diamond and two more clubs.
</p>
<h2>Complexity</h2>
<p>
This is a rare par-zero deal of complexity three.  The spade suit is the only par-zero suit:
</p>
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="KQT3" he="9852" di="J7" cl="A64"/>
<hand seat="W" sp="A64" he="KQT3" di="9852" cl="J7"/>
<hand seat="E" sp="9852" he="J7" di="A64" cl="KQT3"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="J7" he="A64" di="KQT3" cl="9852"/>
</diagram>
<p>
South can make exactly six tricks in any contract.
</p>
</body>
</article>
