<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>Top Tricks</title>
<!--
#
# GIB Input
#
n T72.86543.J.AJ93
e 84.AKJT.6532.Q75
s J65.972.AKQ7.K42
w AKQ93.Q.T984.T86
#
# iDeal Input
#
north is {T72 86543 J AJ93}
east is {84 AKJT 6532 Q75}
south is {J65 972 AKQ7 K42}
west is {AKQ93 Q T984 T86}
-->
<!-- level 4 - spades, hearts, diamonds, clubs -->
<body>
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="T72" he="86543" di="J" cl="AJ93"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="AKQ93" he="Q" di="T984" cl="T86"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="84" he="AKJT" di="6532" cl="Q75"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="J65" he="972" di="AKQ7" cl="K42"/>
</diagram>

<h2>Notrump</h2>
<p>East/West have a running nine tricks, while North/South have eight.
How eight?  North wins the <diamond card="J"/>, then leads the 
<club card="J"/>, forcing East to cover.  South then runs his diamonds and
finesses in clubs against West's <club card="T"/>.
</p><p>
In fact, North/South have the first seven tricks off the top in any contract,
since East/West are forced to follow to three clubs and four diamonds. In
every contract, they can manufacture an eight tricks as well, as we'll see.
</p>
<h2>Spades</h2>
<p>
If East/West declare spades, North/South takes their seven tricks, then
North plays a fourth round of clubs, promoting an eighth trick in trumps
when South ruffs with the <spade card="J"/>.
</p><p>
If North/South declare spades, West just pull trumps and takes the four heart
tricks, for nine defensive tricks.
</p>
<h2>Hearts</h2>
<p>
If East/West declare hearts, North/South again take the top seven tricks, North
pitching three spades on diamonds.  At trick eight,  North exits
passively with a heart.  East/West never score a spade, because North's long
trump keeps East from pulling all of them, and when North gets in, he leads
his last club, promoting another trump for himself.  East/West are left with
the four trump tricks he started with.
</p>
<h2>Diamonds</h2>
<p>
If North/South are on lead, they can take four diamonds
and four clubs, for eight tricks.
</p><p>
If East/West are on lead, they take six top tricks and lead a fourth round of
hearts, South forced to ruff.  Now East/West get two natural trump tricks,
for eight tricks.  (West sheds clubs on East's hearts, so if South doesn't
ruff the fourth heart, East just gives his partner a club ruff.)
</p>
<h2>Clubs</h2>
<p>
As usual, North/South take the first eight tricks.
</p><p>
But if East/West are on lead, they take the first six tricks and promote
a seventh by leading a fourth round of hearts.
</p>
<h2>Post Mortem</h2>
<p>
East/West can't make more than five tricks declaring any contract here.
In hearts or notrumps, only four.
</p><p>
North/South can make as many as six tricks only in clubs and hearts.
</p><p>
The play of leading the club jack from <holding cards="AJ9x"/> opposite 
<holding cards="Kxx"/> is called a "backward finesse," if done by declarer,
or a "surrounding play" if done by the defense.  Peculiar that the
terminology would be so different.
</p>
</body>
</article>
