<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-html40"
	 xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>Introduction</title>
<html:p>Are there any deals where neither side can make any contract?</html:p>
<html:p>This comes up in bridge discussions now and then, and the answer is,
yes.  The easiest example is:</html:p>

<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="AKQJ" he="x" di="xxxx" cl="xxxx"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="xxxx" he="xxxx" di="x" cl="AKQJ"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="xxxx" he="xxxx" di="AKQJ" cl="x"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="x" he="AKQJ" di="xxxx" cl="xxxx"/>
</diagram>
<html:p>
In any contract, the defense can take eight top tricks, which means
that not only can nobody make any contract, but all contracts end up down
two.
</html:p><html:p>
A more typical "rigged" example is:
</html:p>
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="AKQ" he="xxxx" di="Jxx" cl="xxx"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="xxx" he="Jxx" di="AKQ" cl="xxxx"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="Jxx" he="xxx" di="xxxx" cl="AKQ"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="xxxx" he="AKQ" di="xxx" cl="Jxx"/>
</diagram>
<html:p>In spades, East/West start with three rounds of clubs, then three rounds
of diamonds, followed by a fourth round of clubs, which promotes the spade
jack in the East hand.  If East/West declare spades, North/South draw
trumps immediately, killing the promotion.</html:p>
<html:p>In fact, there are many deals of the sort above, where the defense 
takes the first six tricks and then sets up a seventh trick by a
trump promotion of some sort. These are common enough that I devote
the first set of deals to this idea.   It's very rare to have a
situation like the first deal, above, with each side able to simply
take seven or more tricks off the top.
</html:p><html:p>
Srinivasa Damarla sent me a deal with 9-card fits where nobody makes:
</html:p>
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="AKQJ" he="" di="xxxxx" cl="xxxx"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="xxxxx" he="xxxx" di="" cl="AKQJ"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="xxxx" he="xxxxx" di="AKQJ" cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="AKQJ" di="xxxx" cl="xxxxx"/>
</diagram>
<html:p>
It's interesting to note that this is the ultimate case of "wasted values;"
every honor is held opposite a void.  This also might be the worst case for
declarers -
South can be held to five tricks in notrump, clubs and diamonds. In spades,
West starts with four clubs, East ruffing the fourth and taking his diamonds.
West still gets his long spade, holding South to four tricks.  In hearts, 
West again starts with four clubs , but East pitches spades and West exits
with a heart.  East still gets his four diamonds and a long heart, again
holding declarer to four tricks.  So in notrump, having the lead is worth 3
tricks, while in each suit, having the lead is worth 4 tricks.
</html:p>
<html:p>
Another symmetric example in the same vein is:
</html:p>
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="AKQxxx" he="Jxxx" di="" cl="Txx"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="Txx" he="AKQxxx" di="Jxxx" cl=""/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="Jxxx" he="" di="Txx" cl="AKQxxx"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="" he="Txx" di="AKQxxx" cl="Jxxx"/>
</diagram>
<html:p>
Against spades (declared by South) West starts with AKQ of hearts and a heart
ruff by East.  East then cashes his AKQ of clubs, and another club, West
ruffing with the ten, which promotes the jack in East's hand, giving the
defense eight tricks.
</html:p><html:p>
Against hearts, West leads the AKQ of trumps then exits
in trumps.  North can take three spades, but has to give East an entry,
and the defense gets five hearts and three clubs.
</html:p><html:p>
Against diamonds, West starts with two top hearts, then a heart ruff by East,
and three top clubs, followed by a club ruff and a fourth heart, ruffed
by East with the ten - essentially the same promotion as when defending the
spade contract.
</html:p><html:p>
Against clubs, the defense takes three hearts, East pitching diamonds, then
a diamond ruff and three top clubs, ensuring East/West score five trumps
and three hearts.
</html:p><html:p>
Against notrump, West starts with three top hearts, East pitching diamonds,
West then exits a heart to North, and both North and South have only
black suits.  East eventually gets three clubs and a spade, for a total
of six tricks.
</html:p>
<html:h2>Themes</html:h2>
<html:p>
The obvious, perhaps tautological, theme in these deals is 
<html:em>tempo.</html:em>  Indeed, the
<html:a target="_top" href="http://www.bridgeworld.com/glossary/glossa.html">Bridge World's glossary</html:a> defines
<html:em>tempo</html:em> as simply having the lead, but
in most cases, it is used to describe an <html:em>advantage</html:em>
to having the lead. (Nobody says that an endplayed player has a tempo.)
And thus, it is almost tautological to say that these deals cover the
idea of "tempo" in all its glory.
</html:p><html:p>
The tempo can be used for many purposes:
<html:ul>
<html:li> Setting up tricks - this is why we often lead from our longest and
strongest against notrump, to set up our tricks before they set up
theirs.</html:li>
<html:li> Pitching losers - if you hold xx opposite AKQx in one suit
and xxx opposite xxxx in another, you can pitch a loser in the weak
suit on the run of tricks.</html:li>
<html:li> Taking tricks - the converse of pitching losers.  Having the lead
lets us take our tricks before the other side gets to pitch in the
suit(s).</html:li>
<html:li> Trump promotions - if the other side had the lead, they could simply
draw trumps, but with our side on lead, we can manufacture an extra
trump trick.</html:li>
<html:li>  Killing entries - you can force an opponent to use entries in the
wrong order.</html:li>
</html:ul>
</html:p>

In many of the deals we see, we'll see mixes of each type of tempo advantage.
In an extreme example, there is one deal where a single lead has the
simultaneous effect of trump promotion and entry killing.
<html:h2>Par-zero suit distributions</html:h2>
While all of the examples we've seen above are symmetric, the rest of the
deals in this collection are not.  However, given any specific suit
distribution, say:
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="T72"/>
<hand seat="W" sp="A"/><hand seat="E" sp="KQ543"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="J986"/>
          S : T72
 S : A              S : KQ543
          S: J986
</diagram>
<html:p>we might ask whether the symmetric deal:</html:p>
<diagram>
<hand seat="N" sp="T72" he="KQ543" di="J986" cl="A"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="A" he="T72" di="KQ543" cl="J986"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="KQ543" he="J986" di="A" cl="T72"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="J986" he="A" di="T72" cl="KQ543"/>
</diagram>
<html:p>
where every suit is distributed this way, is par-zero.  In this
case, the full symmetric deal is par-zero.  Such a suit distribution
is called par-zero.
</html:p>
<html:p>
In every deal found so far, no matter how assymetric, at lEast
one of the suits is a par-zero suit distribution.  Usually 2 or 3
of them are par-zero distributions.  For example, in <a href="ex24.html">Untitled XIV</a>, only the spade suit distribution is not itself par-zero. 
</html:p>
<html:p>
We define the "complexity" of a par-zero deal by the number of suits in the
deal which are <em>not</em>par-zero suit distributions.  In a symmetric deal,
the complexity is zero.  Most of the deals found are complexity 1 or 2, a
very few are complexity 3.
</html:p>

<html:h2>Finding deals</html:h2>
<html:p>
As with my collections of <a target="_top" href="../tenaces/">Double
Asymmetries</a> and  <a target="_top" href="../badfit/">Bad Fit Deals,</a>
this collection used a combination of two programs to find interesting
examples:
</html:p>
<html:ul>
<html:li> <html:a target="_top" href="/~thomaso/deal/">Deal 3.0</html:a>,
my own flexible dealer and deal filter.</html:li>
<html:li> The double dummy solver from
<html:a target="_top"
        href="http://www.cirl.uoregon.edu/~ginsberg/bridge.html">GIB</html:a>
</html:li>
</html:ul>
<html:p>
In order to cut down on calls to GIB's double-dummy solver, I used some
filters - I rejected deals where either side has a 9-card fit or longer, and
any deals where one side has a significant amount of playing strength.
It is possible that this misses some interesting examples, but some
expediency is necessary.  The algorithm I used found one match out of
every 500,000 deals or so.
</html:p>
<html:h2>Open Question</html:h2>
<html:ul>
<html:li>
Is the deal provided by Srinivasa the worst case?
</html:li>
<html:li>
Are there any par-zero deals with complexity four?  That is, does there
exist any par zero deals where none of the individual suits are par-zero
suits?
</html:li>
</html:ul>

<html:h2>About the analysis</html:h2>
<html:p>
A number of shorthands are taken in the analysis, because there are,
technically, 20 different contracts to analyze per deal - five denominations
(notrump, spades, hearts, diamonds, and clubs) and 4 possible declarers.
</html:p>
<html:p>
In none of the cases I've found is the line of play "positional" - that is,
the same suit lead which sets the contract played by South also sets the
contract when played by North.  So I simply refer to "North/South" as declaring
the contract, rather than being more specific.
</html:p>
<html:p>
I also skip some analysis, for the sake of brevity.  Usually these are
"obvious", but in a few cases, other possible lines are left out.
</html:p>
<html:p>
The last section is filled with deals that are currently unanalyzed.  These
are interesting and sometimes fascination little puzzles you might want to
try to solve.  If you want to write up an analysis for any of these,
I'll include it, with attribution.
</html:p>
<html:p>
As usual, I encourage all feedback, particularly if you find errors in
analysis, but even if I've left in typos or bad grammar.  I'm a bad
copy editor.
</html:p>
</article>
