<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://www.thomasoandrews.com/xmlns/bridge">
<title>A Worst Case?</title>
<author email="bridge@thomasoandrews.com">Thomas Andrews</author>
<programdata program="GIB" href="http://www.gibware.com/">
n J9.65432.K.AQT87
e K.AQT87.65432.J9
s 65432.J9.AQT87.K
w AQT87.K.J9.65432
</programdata>
<programdata program="Deal" href="http://bridge.thomasoandrews.com/deal/">
#
# iDeal Input ( http://bridge.thomasoandrews.com/iDeal/notes.html )
#
north is {QT 9762 J53 9843}
east is {J762 AJT8 7642 A}
south is {A543 KQ4 AKQ T62}
west is {K98 53 T98 KQJ75}
</programdata>
<!-- level 2 - spades, clubs -->
<body>
<diagram id="base">
<hand seat="N" sp="J9" he="65432" di="K" cl="AQT87"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="AQT87" he="K" di="J9" cl="65432"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="K" he="AQT87" di="65432" cl="J9"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="65432" he="J9" di="AQT87" cl="K"/>
</diagram>
<p>
South makes three tricks declaring in either major, and five tricks
in either minor.  South also makes only three tricks in notrump.
That means that, in each suit, having the lead is worth five tricks, while
having the lead in notrump is worth seven tricks.
</p>
<h2>Notrump</h2>
<p>
East/West can run 10 tricks in the majors.  Due to the doubleton jack-nines,
the defense can affort to overtake the stiff kings.
</p>
<h2>Spades and Hearts</h2>
<p>
East/West run the same ten tricks as against notrump, starting with the
five trump tricks.
</p>
<h2>Diamonds or Clubs</h2>
<p>
We'll argue from the point of view of the diamond suit.  The defense
against clubs is just done by swapping.
</p><p>
Against diamonds declare by South, West starts with three top spades,
East pitching two clubs.  Assume North ruffs the third round of spades
with the <diamond card="K"/> in dummy, leading to:
<diagram original="base">
<hand seat="N" sp="" he="65432" di="" cl="AQT87"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp="" he="AQT87" di="65432" cl=""/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="87" he="K" di="J9" cl="65432"/>
<hand seat="S" sp="65" he="J9" di="AQT87" cl="K"/>
</diagram>
</p>
<p>
How does declarer get out of the North hand? If North leads a club,
East ruffs and leads a heart to West's <heart card="K"/>.  West cashes one more
spade, and East ruffs the last round of spades.  East then cashes the
<heart card="A"/> and plays the <heart card="Q"/> at this position:
<diagram original="base">
<hand seat="N" sp=""      he="65"    di=""        cl="AQT"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp=""      he=""      di="J9"      cl="654"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp=""      he="^Q"     di="6543"    cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp=""      he=""      di="AQT87"   cl=""/>
</diagram>
West is assured of a diamond trick, by promotion.
North/South score a total of five tricks - the <diamond card="K"/> and 
four diamond tricks at the end.
</p><p>
So maybe, after ruffing with the <diamond card="K"/>, North should exit with
a heart?  Then West wins, takes the rest of his spade, and gives East a club
ruff for the entry.  East then plays off his top hearts as before.
</p><p>
And if North doesn't ruff the third or fourth spades, West shifts to a
club, East ruffs, takes two high hearts, and leads the <heart card="T"/>
for a slightly queasier promotion:
</p>
<diagram original="base">
<hand seat="N" sp=""          he="6"       di="K"       cl="AQT8"/>
<hand seat="W"  sp="7"         he=""        di="J9"      cl="654"/>
<hand seat="E"  sp=""          he="^T8"      di="6543"    cl=""/>
<hand seat="S" sp="6"         he=""        di="AQT87"   cl=""/>
</diagram>
<p>
East/West have taken the first seven tricks, and South can't keep the
defense from scoring an eighth trick.  Obviously, South must ruff high,
and West pitches the club.  South now cannot ruff his spade loser, and
the diamond king is the only entry to the clubs to pitch the spade loser,
but if declarer uses the diamond entry now, East can ruff a club lead.
</p>
</body>
</article>
